[
  {
    "question": "The abbreviation \"MASPS\" stands for:",
    "feedback": "Minimum Aviation System Performance Standards"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to commercial aircraft operations: In which part of the Operations Manual would you find information about the policy and procedures for the use of TCAS and ACAS?",
    "feedback": "Part A"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which part of the Operations Manual would you find information regarding dangerous goods?",
    "feedback": "Part A"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot flies for an AOC holder, operating complex motor-powered aircraft. In which document are type-related instructions and procedures to be found for the aircraft flown?",
    "feedback": "Operations Manual Part B"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the event of a contingency which required an en-route diversion to an alternate aerodrome across the direction of the prevailing \"NAT\" traffic flow and if prior ATC clearance cannot be obtained an aircraft able to maintain its assigned flight level should :",
    "feedback": "If above FL410, climb or descend 1000 ft, while turning towards the alternate aerodrome."
  },
  {
    "question": "Following take-off, the noise abatement climb procedures specified by the operator is :",
    "feedback": "for the same airplane type, the same for all airports."
  },
  {
    "question": "The authorization for the transport of  hazardous materials is specified on the:",
    "feedback": "air carrier certificate."
  },
  {
    "question": "CO2 type fire extinguishers are fit to fight:  1) Class A fires 2) Class B fires 3) Fires with an electrical origin 4) Special fires - metal, gas, chemical product\nThe combination of all correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1,2,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, an operator shall not operated across areas in which search and rescue would be especially difficult, unless it is equipped with:  1) signalling equipment 2) at least one ELT 3) at least 2 ELTs 4) additional survival equipment for the route to be flown  The combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "A heavy aircraft is making a missed approach, and a light aircraft is using an opposite-direction runway for take-off. What is the minimum separation that should be applied between these two aircraft?",
    "feedback": "3 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "For purpose of wake turbulence separation, what is the ICAO minimum radar separation distance and minimum time if a medium aeroplane (less than 136000 kg and more than 7000 kg) is following directly behind a heavy aeroplane on the approach to the same runway ?",
    "feedback": "9.3 km (5 NM) and 2 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to OPS regulations, the minimum radio communication and navigation equipment for a VFR flight conducted by reference to visual landmarks by day consists of:",
    "feedback": "one radio communication equipment and one transponder"
  },
  {
    "question": "The first part of the EASA OPS apply to:",
    "feedback": "the operation by a state member of the JAA of any civil commercial transport aircraft."
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, an operator shall ensure that the information contained in the aircraft technical log is stored for a minimum period of:",
    "feedback": "36 months"
  },
  {
    "question": "An airplane creates a wake turbulence when :",
    "feedback": "generating lift."
  },
  {
    "question": "The fire extinguisher types which may be used to fight fire on flammable liquids are:\n\n1) H2O\n2) CO2\n3) dry-chemical\n4) Halon\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "A not ETOPS approved twin-engined aeroplane on a commercial air transport operation departs from Athens to Milan. Shortly after departure, visibility in Athens deteriorates and the flight crew decides to select a different take-off alternate. This new take-off alternate must be located within:\n(OEI: One-Engine-Inoperative)",
    "feedback": "One hour flying time, at OEI cruising speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who checks, before flight, that the aircraft's weight is such that flight can be safely made, and that any transported cargo is properly distributed and secured? (Annex 6, Part I)",
    "feedback": "The captain."
  },
  {
    "question": "With reference to the Clean Aircraft Concept, an aircraft may take-off in the following condition:",
    "feedback": "Thin hoar frost on the fuselage"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a commercial air transport flight, when carrying special categories of passengers (SCPs), such as persons with reduced mobility (PRMs), they ....",
    "feedback": "should not be allocated, nor occupy, seats that permit direct access to emergency exits"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft leaves point P (60°N 030°W) on a true heading equal to 090° while the gyro compass, which is assumed to be operating perfectly and without an hourly rate corrector unit, indicates 000°. The aircraft arrives at point Q (62°N 010°W) on a true heading equal to 095°. On the journey from P to Q the gyro compass remains in free gyro mode. If the flight lasted 1 hour 30 minutes, the gyro heading at Q will be :",
    "feedback": "328°."
  },
  {
    "question": "Whenever a potential bird hazard is observed, the commander shall:",
    "feedback": "immediately inform the local ATS unit"
  },
  {
    "question": "Following an explosive decompression and an emergency descent, the maximum altitude without oxygen at which the flight crew efficiency is not impaired is :",
    "feedback": "8000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In EASA AIR OPS, a runway is considered damp when:",
    "feedback": "its surface is not dry, and when surface moisture does not give it a shiny appearance."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, the commander shall not commence take-off:",
    "feedback": "unless the external surfaces are clear of any deposit, except as permitted by Aircraft Flight Manual"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, in order to be operated IFR or at night in aereas with potentially hazardous weather conditions, an aeroplane must be equipped with an airborne weather radar when the aeroplane is:  1) pressurised 2) non-pressurised with a maximum take-off mass of more than 5700 kg 3) non-pressurised with a maximum approved seating configuration of more than 9 seats 4) non-pressurised regardless of weight or seating configuration  The combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which chapter (part) of the Operations Manual would you find information about noise abatement procedures (NAP)?",
    "feedback": "Part B, C"
  },
  {
    "question": "An operator is permitted to use an aircraft with certain items of equipment out of service if this is provided for in:",
    "feedback": "the Minimum Equipment List (MEL) or Master Minimum Equipment List (MMEL)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, an aeroplane whose maximum take off mass exceeds 5700 kg or whose maximum approved passenger seating configuration is greater than 9 seats and less than 200 seats must be equipped with a:",
    "feedback": "crash axe or a crowbar on the flight deck"
  },
  {
    "question": "With regard to smoke and fire in the cabin, which statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "The actions to be taken by the crew may be type specific"
  },
  {
    "question": "Minimum Navigation Performance Specification (MNPS) airspace of the North Atlantic is comprised within :",
    "feedback": "flight levels 285 and 420 from the North parallel 27 to the pole"
  },
  {
    "question": "An operator is performing CAT non-scheduled flights in Spain with an aircraft dry-leased from an owner resident in Greece. The flight and cabin crew hold Part-FCL licences and attestations, respectively, issued by Finland. The operator has its principal place of business in Austria.\nAccording to EU OPS regulations, which Member State shall designate the Competent Authority responsible for the oversight of this operation?",
    "feedback": "Austria"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are a commander of a flight, where an anti-icing and de-icing procedure has been applied. While taxiing for take-off there is a delay, because you have to use a different runway for take-off, but the holdover time is not yet exceeded. What is your next action?",
    "feedback": "You continue to the take-off position and take-off, provided the holdover time is not exceeded"
  },
  {
    "question": "The type of hydroplaning that is most likely to occur at the touch down area located at both ends of the runway is called:",
    "feedback": "viscous"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the Area where the MNPS is applicable, the vertical separation that can be applied between FL 290 and FL410 inclusive is :",
    "feedback": "1 000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In case of an engine exhaust pipe fire while on the ground, you should abort the starting procedure and:",
    "feedback": "carry out a dry cranking"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a night flight, an observer located in the cockpit, seeing an aircraft coming from front left on an approximate opposite parallel track, will first see the:",
    "feedback": "red steady light"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, oxygen masks for use by flight crew members shall be a quick donning type of mask, in pressurised aeroplanes operating at pressure altitudes above:",
    "feedback": "25000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flight crew members on the flight deck shall keep their safety belt fastened:",
    "feedback": "while at their station."
  },
  {
    "question": "If the pitot tube becomes blocked during a descent, the airspeed indicator:",
    "feedback": "under-reads"
  },
  {
    "question": "For the purpose of wake turbulence separation, what is the minimum separation time that is permitted when a light aircraft is taking off behind a heavy aircraft from an intermediate part of the same runway ?",
    "feedback": "3 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of fire extinguisher is used on a magnesium fire?",
    "feedback": "Sand"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flying at FL390, before what cabin altitude must the oxygen drop out masks be automatically presented?",
    "feedback": "15000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to OPS regulations, the correct definition of Window Of Circadian Low (WOCL) is the period between:",
    "feedback": "02.00 hours and 05.59 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following factors should be considered by the operator when establishing minimum flight altitudes?",
    "feedback": "Inaccuracies in altimeter indications"
  },
  {
    "question": "An operator shall ensure that for the duration of each flight or series of flights, relevant information is preserved on the ground. This includes:",
    "feedback": "mass and balance documentation, if required"
  },
  {
    "question": "When an aircraft is subject to unlawful interference, who is responsible for collecting and then transmitting pertinent information on the flight to other States responsible for Air Traffic Service units likely to be concerned with the flight, including the unit at the airport of presumed intended destination? The ......",
    "feedback": "Contracting State presently responsible for providing air traffic services to the aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "A 1211 halon fire-extinguisher can be used for:\n\n1. a paper fire\n2. a fabric fire\n3. an electric fire\n4. a wood fire\n5. a hydrocarbon fire\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to CS 25, if a fuel jettisoning system is required, it must be capable of jettisoning enough fuel within:",
    "feedback": "15 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a night flight, an observer located in the cockpit, seeing an aircraft coming from the front left, will first see the :",
    "feedback": "green steady light"
  },
  {
    "question": "At a given configuration, the wake turbulence of an aeroplane is greater when the aeroplane is:",
    "feedback": "heavy at low airspeed"
  },
  {
    "question": "A runway covered with 4 mm thick water, is said to be:",
    "feedback": "contaminated."
  },
  {
    "question": "For a given ambient temperature and type of de-icing fluid used, in which one of the following types of weather condition will the holdover (protection) time be shortest ?",
    "feedback": "Freezing rain"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a landing approach, the aircraft is subjected to windshear with a decreasing tail wind. In the absence of a pilot action, the aircraft :\n\n1- flies above the glide path\n2- flies below the glide path\n3- has an increasing true airspeed\n4- has a decreasing true airspeed\n\nthe combination of correct statements is :",
    "feedback": "1,3."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the European Regulation on Air Operations, which of the following statements is correct regarding operations under IFR, oder under VFR over routes that can not be navigated by reference to visual landmarks?",
    "feedback": "Aircraft shall be equipped with radio communication and navigation equipment in accordance with the applicable airspace requirements"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an airplane with a tyre pressure of 16 bars, there is a risk of dynamic hydroplaning as soon as :  1- water height is equal to the depth of the tyre grooves. 2- speed is greater than 132 kt. 3- water height is equal to the half of the depth of the tyre grooves. 4- speed is greater than 117 kt.  The combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1 and 2."
  },
  {
    "question": "During a night flight, an observer located in the cockpit, seeing an aircraft coming from front right on an approximate opposite parallel track, will first see the:",
    "feedback": "green light."
  },
  {
    "question": "How should firemen approach a heavy aircraft that has had an aborted takeoff?",
    "feedback": "From the front/rear"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming that the operator is approved by the Authority to transport dangerous goods, the carriage of dangerous goods is allowed, provided that:",
    "feedback": "the operator complies with the technical instructions (ICAO DOC 9284)."
  },
  {
    "question": "During a quick turnaround in Cologne, the ATIS reports an air temperature of -10°C and freezing rain. The aircraft has landed with clear ice under the wings. The flight is only a short time before the next departure.\nWhat shall the Commander do?",
    "feedback": "Order a complete de-ice, following the Clean Aircraft Concept"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where do you find information related to the use of MEL and CDL in the OPS manual?",
    "feedback": "Part A"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regulation (EC) 300/2008 and ICAO Annex 17 address unlawful interference with civil aviation.\nWhat is the primary objective of the Regulation?",
    "feedback": "To establish common rules to protect civil aviation against acts of unlawful interference that jeopardise the security of civil aviation"
  },
  {
    "question": "When can the required noise abatement procedure be disregarded?",
    "feedback": "At PICs discretion where safety is an issue"
  },
  {
    "question": "The application of a type II de-icing fluid on an aircraft on ground will provide a :",
    "feedback": "certain time of protection dependent on the outside air temperature, precipitation and fluid mixture"
  },
  {
    "question": "What kind of information is indicated by 3480 in column 2 (see red circle) of the Dangerous Goods List of the Technical Instructions (ICAO DOC 9284)?",
    "feedback": "UN number"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, the minimum required recent experience for a pilot engaged in a single-pilot operation under IFR or at night shall be :",
    "feedback": "5 IFR flights, including 3 instrument approaches, carried out during the preceding 90 days on the type class of aeroplane in the single-pilot role."
  },
  {
    "question": "The recent experience conditions of a captain assigned to a flight on an aircraft by an operator must not be less than :",
    "feedback": "3 take-offs and 3 landings as pilot in command on this type of aircraft during the last 90 days"
  },
  {
    "question": "The reference document dealing with air transport of hazardous materials is :",
    "feedback": "ICAO Appendix 18"
  },
  {
    "question": "An air traffic unit may request the aircraft to report position when flying east-west south of 70°N between 5°W and 65°W, every:",
    "feedback": "10° of longitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "Under certain conditions, the pilot can take off without following the reduced power take-off procedure. Which of the following is/are such a condition?\n1) Wind shear has been reported2) Horizontal visibility is 3000 m3) The crosswind component is 13 knots4) The tailwind component is 3 knots",
    "feedback": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "The regulatory green navigation light is located on the starboard side, with a coverage angle of :",
    "feedback": "110°."
  },
  {
    "question": "For an airplane with a  tyre pressure of 14 bars, there is a risk of dynamic hydroplaning as soon as the :\n\n1- water height is equal to the depth of the tyre grooves.\n2- speed is greater than 123 kt.\n3- water height is equal to the half of the depth of the tyre grooves.\n4- speed is greater than 95 kt.\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1 and 2."
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, all occupants of flight deck seats on flight deck duty in a non-pressurised aircraft shall be supplied with supplemental oxygen for the entire flight time at pressure altitudes above:",
    "feedback": "10000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, an aeroplane whose maximum approved passenger seating configuration is 301 to 400 seats must be equipped with at least:",
    "feedback": "5 hand fire extinguishers conveniently located in the passenger compartment"
  },
  {
    "question": "A slow decompression may be caused by:  1) a leak in a doorseal during normal pressurized flight 2) loss of a cabin compartment window 3) malfunction of all pressurization systems 4) loss of a cargo-hold door  The combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to OPS regulations what does \"anti-icing\", in the case of ground procedures, mean?",
    "feedback": "A procedure that provides protection against the formation of frost or ice and accumulation of snow on treated surfaces of the aircraft for a limited period of time"
  },
  {
    "question": "When taking-off after a widebody aircraft which has just landed, you should take-off :",
    "feedback": "beyond the point where the aircraft's wheels have touched down."
  },
  {
    "question": "The principle of operation of a fire loop detector is as the temperature increases, the:",
    "feedback": "resistance decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with OPS regulations (Aerodrome Operating Minima), for a Category III A approach, the RVR shall not be less than:",
    "feedback": "200 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "A recent aircraft must be provided with a flight data recorder when its certified take-off gross weight is greater than :",
    "feedback": "5 700 kg"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wake turbulence risk is highest :",
    "feedback": "when a heavy aircraft has just performed a take-off at a closely situated parallel runway with a light crosswind."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to OPS regulations, the maximum daily Flight Duty Period (FDP) can be extended by up to:",
    "feedback": "1 hour"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following may force an aircraft in flight into a ditching situation?",
    "feedback": "A smoke, fire, or fumes situation that becomes uncontrollable"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, the lowest minima to be used by an operator for circling with a category C aeroplane is a meteorological visibility of:",
    "feedback": "2400 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "The term decision height (DH) is used for :",
    "feedback": "a precision approach."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane suffers an explosive decompression at an altitude of 31000 ft . What is the initial action by the operating crew ?",
    "feedback": "to put on oxygen masks"
  },
  {
    "question": "When refueling is being performed while passengers are boarding or disembarking the aircraft, one of the requirements is:",
    "feedback": "the ground area beneath the exits intended for emergency evacuation and slide deployment areas must be kept clear."
  },
  {
    "question": "An airline operator shall make sure that if the aircraft planned for the flight is a performance class B aeroplane, it will be able, throughout its flight route or its alternate route scheduled from this initial route, to reach a climb rate of at least :",
    "feedback": "300ft/min with all engines operating at maximum continuous power."
  },
  {
    "question": "If no meteorological information is available for the destination, the operator must:",
    "feedback": "select two destination alternates"
  },
  {
    "question": "First aid oxygen carried on a pressurised aircraft is used for:",
    "feedback": "passengers or crew when required"
  },
  {
    "question": "In EASA AIR OPS, a runway is considered wet when:  1. it is covered with a quantity of water or loose or slushy snow less than or equal to the equivalent of 3 mm of water. 2. the amount of surface moisture is sufficient to modify its colour but does not give it a shiny appearance. 3. the amount of surface moisture is sufficient to make it reflective, but does not create large stagnant sheets of water. 4. it bears stagnant sheets of water.  The combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following reasons is most likely to force a twin-jet aeroplane to perform an emergency landing?",
    "feedback": "Multiple bird strikes during the take-off that cause an engine failure and erratic operation of the remaining engine"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, a Category III B operations, is a precision instrument approach and landing using ILS or MLS with, a decision height lower than 50 ft, or no decision height and a runway visual range lower than 200 m but no less than :",
    "feedback": "75 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "The holdover time associated with anti-icing and de-icing procedures varies, depending on the prevailing weather conditions and temperatures. The time of the protection will be shortened .......",
    "feedback": "in heavy weather conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "When an aircraft,  having already undergone an anti-icing procedure, must be protected again:",
    "feedback": "First, you must de-ice again  the surface of the airplane, then apply the new layer of anti-icing fluid."
  },
  {
    "question": "For a pressurised aircraft, the first aid oxygen is designed to:",
    "feedback": "provide undiluted oxygen for passengers who, for physiological reasons, might require oxygen following a cabin depressurisation"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, an operator shall ensure that each cabin crew member is at least:",
    "feedback": "18 years of age"
  },
  {
    "question": "On board a non-pressurized aircraft, 10% of the passengers must be supplied with oxygen throughout the period of flight, reduced by 30 minutes, during which the pressure altitude is between :",
    "feedback": "10 000 ft and 13 000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What kind of dangerous goods is specified by the label?",
    "feedback": "Flammable solids"
  },
  {
    "question": "Area Navigation (RNAV) and Required Navigation Performance (RNP) are fundamentally similar but they differ in the requirements for on-board performance monitoring and alerting. Despite the differences in the requirements, renaming RNP routes to RNAV routes would incur huge costs.\nAs a result, according to ICAO DOC 9613, RNAV 10 retains which RNP designation?",
    "feedback": "10"
  },
  {
    "question": "On the diagram where :\n\nNt = True North\nNm = Magnetic North\nNg = Grid North\n\nIf the magnetic variation is equal to 65°W and if the grid variation is equal to 4°E, the correct arrangement of the different north is :",
    "feedback": "3"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Standards and Recommended Practices contained in ICAO Annex 6, Part I, are applicable to ....",
    "feedback": "the operation of aeroplanes by operators authorised to conduct international commercial air transport operations"
  },
  {
    "question": "The information concerning dangerous products that passengers may carry, are listed in the :",
    "feedback": "ICAO document named \"Technical safety instructions for the air transportation of dangerous products\""
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft flying at flight level 370 (FL 370) in MNPS Airspace is unable to continue flight in accordance with its air traffic control clearance, but is able to maintain FL 370. Due to a total loss of communications capability, it is unable to obtain a revised clearance from ATC.\n\nThe aircraft should offset from the assigned route by 15 NM and:",
    "feedback": "climb or descend 500 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following does not apply concerning an explosive decompression during a flight at FL410?\n1) Oxygen is not necessary due to wind which is caused by the hole2) Pain inside the ears3) Limited visibility in the cabin4) Unsecured items located close to the area are prone to be ejected",
    "feedback": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the passenger briefing for a flight requiring life jackets, the passengers shall be instructed to inflate their life jackets:",
    "feedback": "when outside the aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following should be contained in an operator's security search procedure?\n1) Aircraft-specific checklist2) Actions in the event of discovery of a bomb3) Removal procedures for suspicious articles4) Sabotage procedures",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "MNPS is the abbreviation for:",
    "feedback": "Minimum Navigation Performance Specification."
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, a public address system is required to operate an aeroplane with a maximum approved passenger seating configuration of more than:",
    "feedback": "19"
  },
  {
    "question": "When does the engine fire warning light go out?",
    "feedback": "When the fire has been extinguished"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure\nAt 18:00 your aircraft is sprayed with TYPE I anti-ice fluid. Outside conditions are: very light snow and light rain with an air temperature of -4°C. What is the holdover time in these conditions?",
    "feedback": "2 min to 5 min"
  },
  {
    "question": "If airworthiness documents do not shown any additionnal correction factor for landing performance determination on a wet runway, the landing distance shall be increased by:",
    "feedback": "15%."
  },
  {
    "question": "The Control Display Unit (CDU) of an Inertial Navigation System (INS), indicates the following information :\n\n- Desired track (DTK) = 100°\n- Track (TK) = 120°\n\nBased on this information the:",
    "feedback": "Track Error Angle (TKE) is right (R)"
  },
  {
    "question": "When there is a risk of hydroplaning the pilot of an aeroplane:",
    "feedback": "should make a positive landing and apply maximum reverse thrust and brakes as quicky as possible"
  },
  {
    "question": "While approaching a mountainous airfield, the captain of a transport aircraft notices a fast and high increase in the indicated airspeed without any change in the preselected engine and attitude parameters. The preceding crews had  reported the occurrence of windshears in final phase. you must :",
    "feedback": "maintain the aircraft on the glide path, accept a positive speed deviation, monitor the speed evolution."
  },
  {
    "question": "During take-off an aircraft hits a bird. Due to control vibrations a landing must be made immediately. Following this incident the pilot :",
    "feedback": "must file a Bird Strike report"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a transoceanic and polar flight, the chart precession is a rotation in degrees, for a moving aircraft, of the gyro North with respect to the :",
    "feedback": "grid North for a given chart"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, following a decompression, the maximum pressure altitude at which each member of the flight crew on flight deck duty are able to fly with no supplemental oxygen with no flight time limitation is:",
    "feedback": "10000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "When anti-icing has been applied, when must you make sure it is still active?",
    "feedback": "At brake release for take-off"
  },
  {
    "question": "A holder of an Air Operator Certificate (AOC) issued by an EASA Member State is required to establish procedures to minimise the effect of aircraft noise for each aeroplane type it operates. These procedures must cover ......",
    "feedback": "departure and arrival/approach"
  },
  {
    "question": "Each Contracting State concerned with an act of unlawful interference shall provide all pertinent information concerning the security aspects of the act as soon as practicable after the act is resolved. \nTo whom shall this report be provided?",
    "feedback": "ICAO"
  },
  {
    "question": "A crew member is allowed to carry safety matches:\n\n1) on himself/herself\n2) in his/her hand luggage\n3) in his/her checked luggage\n4) for his/her own use\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "In EASA AIR OPS, a runway is referred to as contaminated when more than 25 % of the required runway surface is covered with the one of the following elements:  1. a water film sufficiently thick to give a shiny appearance to the runway. 2. a water film or loose or slushy snow equivalent to more than 3 mm of water. 3. compacted snow (a solid mass which may not be compacted further). 4. ice, including wet ice. 5. moist grass.  The combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, an aeroplane whose maximum approved passenger seating configuration is 200 must be equipped with:",
    "feedback": "3 hand fire extinguisher in the passenger compartment"
  },
  {
    "question": "On what type of fire would a CO2 extinguisher be most effective?",
    "feedback": "Electrical"
  },
  {
    "question": "The minimum longitudinal separation of two aircraft flying in NAT airspace at the same Flight Level, on the same track and with the same Mach number is:",
    "feedback": "15 minutes."
  },
  {
    "question": "A minimum time route is a route calculated for:",
    "feedback": "a given flight from departure to destination."
  },
  {
    "question": "During a climb after take-off from a contaminated runway, if the total pressure probe of the airspeed indicator is blocked, the pilot finds that indicated airspeed :",
    "feedback": "increases steadily"
  },
  {
    "question": "Thunderstorm activity takes place in the vicinity of an airport. During the take-off roll, the crew notices a rapid build-up of airspeed. Soon after lift-off, the Ground Proximity Warning activates and the aircraft loses altitude. The most probable cause is a microburst which, by the start of the take-off roll, has formed ......",
    "feedback": "on the RWY, ahead of the aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "An air traffic units may request the aircraft to report position when flying east-west north of 70°N between 10°W and 50°W, every:",
    "feedback": "20° of longitude."
  },
  {
    "question": "Following an act of unlawful interference, who shall, without delay, submit a report of such an act to the relevant authority?",
    "feedback": "The Pilot-in-Command"
  },
  {
    "question": "The correct statement about extinguishing agents on board aircraft is :",
    "feedback": "Halon is an effective extinguishing agent for use in aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the MNPS (Minimum Navigation Performance Specification) area, a pilot should first of all take the following action in the event of a failure of the last inertial navigation system:",
    "feedback": "notify Control and wait for a reply within a reasonable time."
  },
  {
    "question": "One of the correct actions to take in the case of overheated brakes after landing or an aborted take-off is to....",
    "feedback": "consider where to park the aircraft as regards proximity to other aircraft, buildings, etc."
  },
  {
    "question": "One of the main characteristics of windshear is that it :",
    "feedback": "can occur at any altitude in both the vertical and horizontal planes"
  },
  {
    "question": "On board a pressurized aircraft, a flight shall be undertaken only if the aircraft is provided with an oxygen reserve enabling all the crew members and part of the passengers to be supplied with oxygen in the event of a cabin depressurization, throughout the flight period after the first 30 minutes, during which the pressure altitude is greater than :",
    "feedback": "10 000 ft."
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, an aeroplane whose maximum approved passenger seating configuration is 7 to 30 seats must be equipped with at least:",
    "feedback": "1 hand fire extinguisher conveniently located in the passenger compartment"
  },
  {
    "question": "The wake turbulence is greater when the aircraft has a :",
    "feedback": "high weight, low speed, gear and flaps up"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the European Regulation on Air Operations as applicable to Commercial Air Transport operations. Flight time specification schemes shall state the conditions for extensions to the maximum basic daily FDP due to in-flight rest. These extensions shall take into account the ....",
    "feedback": "augmentation of the basic flight crew"
  },
  {
    "question": "You will use a water fire-extinguisher (straight jet) on a fire of :\n\n1 - solids (fabric, carpet, ...)\n2 - liquids (ether, gasoline, ...)\n3 - gas\n4 - metals (sodium, ...)\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1"
  },
  {
    "question": "Halon or equivalent fire extinguishers can be used in case of fire fighting in an aircraft:",
    "feedback": "in the cockpit and cargo holds"
  },
  {
    "question": "For commercial air transport operations, who approves the method for establishing minimum flight altitudes?",
    "feedback": "The Competent Authority"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, when a flight data recorder is required, it must stop automatically to record the data:",
    "feedback": "after the aircraft is unable to move by its own power"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, an operator must ensure that the MDH for a VOR/DME approach is not lower than:",
    "feedback": "250 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "A Minimum Obstacle Clearance Altitude (MOCA) is defined as 8300 feet. The maximum terrain or obstacle in the area of applicability of this MOCA is ....",
    "feedback": "6280 feet"
  },
  {
    "question": "DOC 4444 (ICAO) establishes, that wake turbulence separation minima shall be based on a grouping of aircraft types into three categories according to the maximum certificated take-off mass.\nHeavy (H) Category, are all aircraft types of :",
    "feedback": "136 000 Kg or more"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the figure below:\nFlight in a twin-engine aircraft from Paris to Washington.\nETOPS authorization: 105 minutes at 420 kts\nTrack A: time 8 hours 3 minutes\nTrack B: time 8 hours 10 minutes\nTrack C: time 8 hours 15 minutes\nTrack D: time 8 horus 20 minutes\n\nGive that the three alternate aerodromes taken into account are Shannon, Santa Maria, and St. John, the track to be chosen between will be:",
    "feedback": "track C."
  },
  {
    "question": "Following an emergency landing, the Commander of a flight should ......",
    "feedback": "determine if an immediate evacuation is necessary or if the aircraft can safely taxi off the runway"
  },
  {
    "question": "Information concerning emergency evacuation procedures shall be found in the:",
    "feedback": "operations manual"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are routing towards DOGAL in order to follow NAT track G to Canada as filed. The oceanic clearance is requested and provided as follows:\n\"Oceanic clearance with a reroute, Shanwick Oceanic clears EASA 104 to TORONTO PEARSON via PIKIL MAT track D\"\nWhat has to be considered?",
    "feedback": "Apply the applicable SOPs for a reroute to minimise the threat of gross navigation errors"
  },
  {
    "question": "The time needed for the dissipation of a turbulent wake created by a wide-body aircraft during take-off is about:",
    "feedback": "3 minutes."
  },
  {
    "question": "The maximum validity of a SNOWTAM is :",
    "feedback": "8 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under which of the following circumstances is compliance with noise abatement approach procedures required?\n1) ceiling below 500 ft above aerodrome level2) recent rain with runway assessed as clear and dry3) visibility 2500 m4) snow- or ice-contaminated runway5) Crosswind component, including gusts, 10 knots",
    "feedback": "2, 3, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a light crosswind (approximately 5 kt) from the right behind an aeroplane taking off:",
    "feedback": "The right wake turbulence stays approximately on the runway."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following risks can be identified in a SNOWTAM?\n1) Snow2) Water3) Lightning4) Oil spills5) Windshear",
    "feedback": "1, 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the requirement for the issue of an AOC?",
    "feedback": "Not already hold an AOC issued by another authority."
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to Jeppesen GSPRM, VFR Chart ED-4\nA pilot is planning a VFR flight from Schönberg aerodrome EDPK (N48°03', E012°30') to Grabenstätt aerodrome (N47°51', E012°33'). What is the possible hazard to be expected?",
    "feedback": "Increased risk of bird strike"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a commercial flight at 2000 ft AGL with a multi-engined piston aircraft, both engines catch fire, and the aircraft is not equipped with engine fire extinguishing systems. What would be an appropriate course of action, unless stated otherwise in the AFM?",
    "feedback": "Carry out the engine fire checklist to shut down the engines, prepare for an immediate forced landing, and extend the flaps only when it is assured that the emergency landing area can be reached"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\nSNOWTAM 0183A) ESSAB) 01230720C) 01LF) 5/5/5G) 02/02/02H) 4/3/3N) 25/MEDIUM 02 MM CONTAMINATION 50 PERCENT\nC) 01RF) 5/5/5G) 01/02/02H) 5/5/4N) 25/MEDIUM 02 MM CONTAMINATION 50 PERCENT\nC) 08F) 6/6/5G) 01/01/01H) 4/4/4N) 25/MEDIUM 01MM CONTAMINATION 25 PERCENT\nR) 25/POOR 08MM CONTAMINATION 100 PERCENTT) DE ICING FLUIDS ON RWY 01L 01R AND 08\nWhich landing runway provides the best estimated surface friction?",
    "feedback": "Runway 01R"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under what conditions can the choice of runway disregard any noise abatement approach procedures?\n1) Crosswind > 15 knots2) Tailwind >5 knots3) Wind shear and thunderstorm reported",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which chapter (part) of the Operations Manual would you find information on performance data?",
    "feedback": "Part B"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with ICAO and PANS RAC procedures, which letter should be entered into a flight plan to denote an aeroplane which has a weight of less than 136000 kg but greater than 7000 kg :",
    "feedback": "M"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to commercial aircraft operations: In what part of the Operations Manual would you find type specific information?",
    "feedback": "Part B"
  },
  {
    "question": "The primary purpose of allowing aircraft conducting oceanic flight in the NAT HLA to fly self-selected lateral offsets (SLOP) is to....",
    "feedback": "mitigate against collision risk"
  },
  {
    "question": "What kind of dangerous goods is specified by the label?",
    "feedback": "Oxidising substances"
  },
  {
    "question": "Aeroplane wake turbulence during take off starts when:",
    "feedback": "the nose wheel lifts the runway"
  },
  {
    "question": "The actions required by the cabin crew on encountering smoke in the passenger cabin include:",
    "feedback": "Identify source of smoke, isolate any appropriate electrical and/or galley equipment, if possible move passengers away from the source, dispense wet towels if available"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following might be a noticeable effect clearly indicating a rapid decompression has just occurred during level flight?",
    "feedback": "Loud bang or similar noise"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, a windshield wiper or equivalent means to maintain a clear portion of the windshield during precipitation is required at each pilot station to operate an aeroplane with a:",
    "feedback": "maximum certificated take-off mass of more than 5700 kg"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, when a commercial transport passenger aeroplane or helicopter is equipped with a door in the flight crew compartment area, this door must include:",
    "feedback": "a locking system to prevent any unauthorized access."
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight across the Atlantic Ocean in a commercial multi-engined jet aircraft, a sudden fuel leak is experienced and the only option is to ditch the aircraft. Unless the Aeroplane Flight Manual (AFM) or the Operations Manual state otherwise, what would be the most appropriate configuration of the aircraft?\nMinimum approach speed, ......",
    "feedback": "gear up and maximum flap"
  },
  {
    "question": "To fight a fire in an air-conditioned class E cargo hold, the correct initial action is to:",
    "feedback": "shut off the ventilating airflow within the affected compartment"
  },
  {
    "question": "A light aircraft is flying directly behind a large, wide-bodied aircraft that is performing a slow flight manoeuvre. The wind is calm. The light aircraft is flying slightly below the large aircraft. When the light aircraft enters the wake of the larger aircraft, it is expected to experience ......",
    "feedback": "a strong downdraft with potential roll"
  },
  {
    "question": "In VFR public transport on an aircraft for which the flight manual inidicates a minimum crew of one pilot, when do the regulations require the presence of a second pilot ?",
    "feedback": "never."
  },
  {
    "question": "During a de-icing/anti-icing procedure carried out in two steps, the holdover time starts:",
    "feedback": "at the beginning of the second step (anti-icing step)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot encounters wind shear on final approach. What should be done to most safely escape it?",
    "feedback": "Aggressively apply full thrust using all of the aircraft's performance"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to Annex 6, \"RNP type\" is defined as a containment value expressed as a distance in ...(i)... from the intended position within which flights would be for at least ...(ii)... of the total flying time.",
    "feedback": "(i) nautical miles\n(ii) 95%"
  },
  {
    "question": "The minimum rest period for flight crew before undertaking a Flight Duty Period (FDP) at home base is at least:",
    "feedback": "12 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "After a fast landing, hot brakes are suspected. What action should be taken?",
    "feedback": "Release the brakes and approach the aeroplane from the front or rear"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements best describes the term \"unidentified baggage\" in accordance with ICAO Annex 17?\nBaggage at an airport ......",
    "feedback": "with or without a baggage tag, which is neither picked up by nor associated with a passenger"
  },
  {
    "question": "According with the \"noise abatement take-off and climb procedure NADP 2\", as established in DOC 8168 - Ops Volume 1, part V, aircraft must climb at V2 + 10 to 20 kt, until reaching :",
    "feedback": "800 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to the picture below:\n\nThe inertial navigation system (INS) indicates:\nPosition: 71° 55.1'N 094°55.3'W\nDrift: 6°L (left)\nThe route followed in order to return to the VOR station is the meridian of the VOR station used:\nRESOLUTE BAY (74°43.6'N 094°55.3W), this VOR has North set on the local geographic meridian.\nThe gyro compass has just been reset to Grid North (chart used: polar stereographic chart, grid parallel to zero meridian, Grid North in the direction of geographic North Pole).\nThe correct representation of the RMI VOR/DME is at this moment:\n(the distance DME is in the box)",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS (Aerodrome Operating Minima), the Category III A Operation, is a precision instrument approach and landing using ILS or MLS with a decision height lower than 100 feet an RVR (runway visual range) no less than :",
    "feedback": "200 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to OPS regulations, \"airport standby\" will count in full for the purposes of cumulative:",
    "feedback": "Duty hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "Company A and Company B sign a dry-lease contract. Company A leases the aircraft from Company B and they register them with the Competent Authority so that the aircraft now have the national registration. The pilots are ready to fly the aircraft when it becomes apparent that the navigation database of the FMS is not the same as the database of Company A.\nAre the pilots allowed to commence the flight?",
    "feedback": "Yes, as long as the navigation database is current and all the procedures are loaded"
  },
  {
    "question": "In case of landing on a flooded runway and in heavy rain :\n\n1. you increase your approach speed,\n2. you land firmly in order to obtain a firm contact of the wheels with the runway and immediately land  your nose gear,\n3. you decrease your approach speed,\n4. you use systematically all the lift dumper devices,\n5. you land as smoothly as possible,\n6. you brake energically.\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is :",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main advantage of Halon 1301 over CO2 for extinguishing an aircraft cabin fire?",
    "feedback": "Halon 1301 can extinguish a fire with much lower concentration than is required for CO2, and it will not deprive the occupants of the cabin of the needed oxygen"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which separation will be provided if Reduced Vertical Separation Minimum (RVSM) is used when operating in MNPS airspace?",
    "feedback": "60 NM lateral and 1000 ft vertical."
  },
  {
    "question": "In a descent, an aircraft is landing into a rapidly increasing tailwind due to wind shear. What will most likely happen?",
    "feedback": "The aircraft will fly below the glideslope"
  },
  {
    "question": "A flight from Europe to Canada is being planned on a large twin-engined jet transport aeroplane. During the pre-flight preparation, a technical issue occurs which only affects the ETOPS status of the aeroplane. The flight must now be operated as NON-ETOPS. What implications does this have to the conduct of the flight? The pilots ....",
    "feedback": "can only follow the planned route if the aeroplane remains within 1 hour, at the One Engine Inoperative cruising speed, of a suitable alternate aerodrome"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an aeroplane with a tyre pressure of 16 bars, there is a risk of dynamic hydroplaning as soon as the:",
    "feedback": "speed is greater than 138 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "The minimum time track is a track defined for :",
    "feedback": "a given travel"
  },
  {
    "question": "In case of a serious threat based on the presence of a bomb on board a pressurized aircraft and disregarding any fuel considerations:",
    "feedback": "you descend to the flight level corresponding to the indicated cabin altitude or the safety altitude if higher and take preventive steps by putting yourself in a landing approach configuration."
  },
  {
    "question": "The frequency designated for VHF air to air communications when out of range of  VHF ground stations in NAT region is :",
    "feedback": "123.45 MHz."
  },
  {
    "question": "The minimum rest period for flight crew before undertaking a Flight Duty Period (FDP) away from the home base is....",
    "feedback": "at least as long as the preceding duty period, or 10 hours, whichever is greater"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a polar stereographic chart whose grid is parallel with the Greenwich meridian in the direction of the true North pole, the \"true\" orientation of the great circle linking point 62°N 010°E to point 66°N 050°W is 305°. The grid route at the starting point of this great circle is :",
    "feedback": "295°."
  },
  {
    "question": "The coverage angle of the regulatory red position light, continuously lit in flight and located at the tip of the left wing is :",
    "feedback": "110°"
  },
  {
    "question": "An IFR flight is flying from Athens to Milan. The weather at the destination is below the applicable minima. The pilot may not take off unless the weather at the expected time of (1) .... at (2) .... is above the applicable minima.",
    "feedback": "(1) arrival, (2) the alternates"
  },
  {
    "question": "The coverage angle of the regulatory red position light, continuously lit in flight and located at the left side is :",
    "feedback": "110°"
  },
  {
    "question": "The \"NO SMOKING\" sign must be illuminated :",
    "feedback": "when oxygen is being supplied in the cabin."
  },
  {
    "question": "A crew is on a quick turnaround at Oslo Gardermoen, Norway. The outside air temperature is -6°C and there is light snow falling. The pilots receive a message from their company Operations Department requesting them to get airborne without delay.\nWhat should the Pilot-in-Command consider?",
    "feedback": "The prevailing weather conditions are such that the aircraft must be de-iced and anti-iced before take-off, even if this results in a delay"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the planning minima for a destination aerodrome. For which of the following approaches would you take a ceiling into account?\n1) non-precision approach2) precision approach3) circling approach",
    "feedback": "1, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "During preparation for your flight, you find that your autopilot is inoperative. Following the OM, you decide to consult the MEL for your aircraft in section 22-01A. Can you carry out a CAT II instrument approach, within the requirements of the MEL?",
    "feedback": "No, at least one autopilot is required to carry out this type of approach"
  },
  {
    "question": "A light aircraft pilot is approaching an aerodrome with the intention to land. ATC gives the pilot the choice of the landing runway and advises that the necessary separation will be provided. Given the following wind and traffic information per runway, which runway should the pilot choose to mitigate, in the best possible way, for a potential wake turbulence encounter?\nRunway 33R: Wind is northerly at 10 kts and the landing is behind a helicopterRunway 33L: Wind is northerly at 10 kts and the landing is behind a light fixed-wing aircraftRunway 21: Wind is variable at 3 kts, and the landing is behind a B777Runway 03: Wind is calm, and the landing is behind an A318",
    "feedback": "Runway 33L"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, an aircraft must be equipped with an audio selector panel accessible to each required flight crew member:",
    "feedback": "when operating under IFR"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the planning minima for a destination aerodrome. For which of the following approaches would you take a ceiling not into account?\n1) non-precision approach2) precision approach3) circling approach",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "If obliged to jettison part of the fuel in flight, it would be better to do so:",
    "feedback": "in a straight line and at a relatively high flight level."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is the correct definition of \"commercial air transport operation\" according to ICAO Annex 6 Part I?",
    "feedback": "An aircraft operation involving the transport of passengers, cargo or mail for remuneration or hire"
  },
  {
    "question": "A fire occurs in a wheel and immediate action is required to extinguish it. The safest extinguishant to use is:",
    "feedback": "Dry powder"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to OPS regulations what does \"de-icing\", in the case of ground procedures, mean?",
    "feedback": "A procedure by which frost, ice, snow or slush is removed from an aircraft in order to provide uncontaminated surfaces"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following de-/anti-ice fluids are available, according to ICAO DOC 9640?",
    "feedback": "Types I, II, III, and IV"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with OPS regulations, the amount of oxygen onboard a non-pressurised aircraft must be enough to feed the cabin crew members and all the passengers for the entire flight time at pressure altitudes above:",
    "feedback": "13000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Tip vortices which are responsible for wake turbulence appear as soon as the following is established :",
    "feedback": "lift"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, the minimum number of hand fire extinguishers to be located in the passenger compartment of an aircraft with a maximum approved passenger seating configuration of 31 is:",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "After a landing, with overweight and overspeed conditions, the tyres and brakes are extremely hot. The fireguards should approach the landing gear tyres:",
    "feedback": "only from front or rear side."
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, an aeroplane whose maximum approved passenger seating configuration greater than 600 seats must be equipped with at least:",
    "feedback": "8 hand fire extinguishers conveniently located in the passenger compartment"
  },
  {
    "question": "After an incident, the FDR recordings must be kept for:",
    "feedback": "60 days."
  },
  {
    "question": "Given the information, choose the lowest possible flap setting for landing on a wet runway, in order to avoid dynamic hydroplaning. The landing performance calculation is based on immediate and maximum brake application after main-gear touchdown.\nLanding Mass: 45000 kgTyre pressure: 200 psi",
    "feedback": "Flaps 30"
  },
  {
    "question": "When a LIGHT aircraft is landing behind a MEDIUM aircraft, the wake turbulence non-radar minimum time approach separation, according with DOC 4444 (ICAO), shall be :",
    "feedback": "3 MIN"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, 100% of the passengers in a non-pressurised aircraft shall be supplied with supplemental oxygen for the entire flight time at pressure altitudes above:",
    "feedback": "13 000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, an aeroplane with a maximum approved passenger seating configuration of more than 61 seats, must have in its passenger compartment(s) at least 3 hand fire extinguishers including:",
    "feedback": "2 Halon fire extinguishers or equivalent"
  },
  {
    "question": "The number of emergency exits in transport aircraft:",
    "feedback": "must be arranged to allow all passengers and all crew members to leave the aircraft within 90 seconds through 50 % of the available emergency exits."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS and assuming the following circumstances:\n- a Category A aeroplane- an aerodrome equipped with runway edge lighting, centre line lighting and multiple RVR information- an acceptable alternate aerodrome is available\nWhat is the minimum RVR value for take-off?",
    "feedback": "150 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "Aircraft operating under VFR over routes navigated by reference to visual landmarks require radio communication equipment that, under normal radio propagation conditions, allows communication with....",
    "feedback": "ATC from any point in controlled airspace within which flights are intended"
  },
  {
    "question": "A minimum time track is a :",
    "feedback": "track determined according to wind conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Master Minimum Equipment List (MMEL), if this exists, is established by:",
    "feedback": "the manufacturer of the aircraft, and accepted by the Authority"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot flies for an AOC holder. Where will he find information on the AOC holders authorised areas of operation, aerodromes and route structure?",
    "feedback": "Part C"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to OPS regulations, an operator shall not operate an aeroplane carrying at least one passenger, unless at least one cabin crew member is included in the crew, when the maximum approved passenger seating configuration is more than:",
    "feedback": "19"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of fire extinguisher would be used on a propane fire?",
    "feedback": "Dry powder"
  },
  {
    "question": "In NAT HLA airspace, in case of need to establish communication with nearby aircraft, the backup inter-pilot air-to-air VHF frequency is:",
    "feedback": "123.450 MHz"
  },
  {
    "question": "In addition to informing each State, whose citizens are known to be on board  an aircraft, the State of the country in which an aircraft has landed after an act of unlawful interference must immediately notify the :",
    "feedback": "State of Registry of the aircraft, the State of the operator and ICAO"
  },
  {
    "question": "The correct color for hand held fire extinguisher labels is:",
    "feedback": "black for CO2"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the EASA AIR OPS rules, the route of a twin-engined aircraft with a maximum certificated take-off mass exceeding 8618 kg or a maximum approved seating configuration of more than 19 passagers must be planned in such a way that on one engine an appropriate aerodrome can be reached within :",
    "feedback": "60 minutes at the cruise speed, one engine inoperative."
  },
  {
    "question": "You plan to fly from point A (60°N 010°E) to point B (60°N 020°E). The gyro North of the gyro compass, assumed to be operating perfectly, with no rate correction device, is aligned with the true North of point A. The constant gyro heading to be followed when starting from A given that the flight time scheduled is 1h30 min with a zero wind, is equal to :",
    "feedback": "076°."
  },
  {
    "question": "Viscous hydroplaning occurs primary if the runway is covered with a thin film of water and:",
    "feedback": "is very smooth and dirty."
  },
  {
    "question": "What action should be taken when following an engine failure procedure after take-off whilst following NADP 1?",
    "feedback": "The pilot has authority to disregard the noise abatement procedure"
  },
  {
    "question": "The safety precautions to be taken when using 100% medical oxygen are:\n\n1) refrain from smoking\n2) avoid sparks\n3) avoid operation of radio communication equipment\n4) operate oxygen system shut off valves slowly\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "At takeoff the maximum mass of the aeroplane shall be:",
    "feedback": "not more than that which would enable compliance with any noise abatement procedure."
  },
  {
    "question": "When leaving the MNPS oceanic control area for a domestic controlled area, the pilot has to:",
    "feedback": "maintain the Mach number previously assigned up to the last position shown in the oceanic clearance."
  },
  {
    "question": "The braking efficiency is a piece of information presenting itself in the form of a :",
    "feedback": "combination of the terms: poor, medium, good."
  },
  {
    "question": "A category III A precision approach (CAT III A) is an approach which may be carried out with a runway visual range of at least :",
    "feedback": "200 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "A crew are about to take off from Paris, France to Washington, USA, at the maximum Performance-Limited Take-Off Mass. Just before V1 during the take-off roll, a master caution indicates a serious engine malfunction. The take-off is aborted with maximum braking, but without the use of reverse thrust. As soon as the aircraft comes to a stop, a brake temperature warning is observed.\nWhat is the correct action by the pilots?",
    "feedback": "Stop the aircraft on the runway, do not apply the parking brake and request fire vehicles to attend because of the possibility of a brake fire"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which part of the Operations Manual would you find information about training matters?",
    "feedback": "Part A, D"
  },
  {
    "question": "In case of a hi-jack, the squawk code is :",
    "feedback": "7500"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is re-positioning from Europe to Canada, and it is planned to enter the NAT HLA at DOGAL and follows westbound track G which begins there. 20 minutes before reaching DOGAL, one of the aircraft's two FMSs fails, and cannot be reset. Which of the following must the pilots do?",
    "feedback": "Remain outside NAT HLA unless ATC approves a reroute via GOMUP-KFV-OZN and onwards"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following sets of conditions is the least likely to attract flocks of birds ?",
    "feedback": "long grass"
  },
  {
    "question": "A warning device alerts the crew in case of an excessive cabin altitude. The warning must be triggered on reaching the following altitude:",
    "feedback": "10000 ft (approx. 3000 m)"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS (Aerodrome Operating Minima), an operator must ensure that system minima for \"non-precision approach procedures\", which are based upon the use of ILS without glidepath (LLZ only), VOR NDB, SRA, and VDF are no lower than MDH following value with:",
    "feedback": "NDB facility, lowest MDH=350 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "At 18:00 your aircraft is sprayed with anti-ice type II fluid, concentration 75/25. Conditions are freezing drizzle and the outside air temperature is -5°C. Your departure time is 18:25 and the new weather conditions are: Temerpature -4°C and with light snow. In these new conditions, the holdover time...",
    "feedback": "is expired"
  },
  {
    "question": "The MNPS (Minimum Navigation Performance Specification) airspace extends from :",
    "feedback": "27° North to 90° North."
  },
  {
    "question": "According with DOC 4444 (ICAO), a wake turbulence non-radar separation minima of 3 minutes shall be applied :",
    "feedback": "to LIGHT aircraft taking-off behind a MEDIUM aircraft from an intermediate part of parallel runway separated by less 760 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "In an aeroplane, each crew member shall be properly secured by all safety belts and harnesses provided:\n\n1) during taxiing\n2) during takeoff\n3) during landing\n4) whenever deemed necessary by the commander in the interest of safety\n5) during other phases of flight\n\nSelect the correct regrouping of the statements:",
    "feedback": "2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Without ETOPS approval, an operator shall not operate a two-engined Class A aeroplane with a maximum approved passenger seating configuration of 20 or more over a route which contains a point further from an adequate aerodrome, at a distance flown:",
    "feedback": "in 60 minutes at the one engine inoperative cruise speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "The best extinguishing product for a wheel fire is:",
    "feedback": "dry powder"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Minimum Equipment List (MEL) defines the equipment on which certain in-flight failures can be allowed and the conditions under which this allowance can be accepted . The MEL is drawn up by :",
    "feedback": "the operator and may be more restrictive than the Master Minimum Equipment List (MMEL)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Shortly before touchdown at a busy airport you hear a few soft bangs coming from the aircraft's nose. After a normal landing and whilst exiting the runway to the taxiway you observe that the airspeed indicator still indicates an airspeed close to your landing reference speed.\nAn immediate valid action with respect to safety at this airport would be to:",
    "feedback": "Notify ATC of a possible bird strike"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the event of an en-route HF communication failure in an MNPS (Minimum Navigation Performance Specification) airspace, the appropriate VHF frequency for air-air communications is :",
    "feedback": "123.450 MHz."
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, for a pressurised aeroplane, during and following an emergency descent, all occupants of flight deck seats on flight deck duty shall be supplied with a minimum supplemental oxygen quantity:  1) in order to maintain a supply throughout the entire flight time where the cabin altitude pressure is greater than 13000 ft 2) in order to maintain a supply throughout the entire flight time where the cabin altitude pressure is greater than 10000 ft and smaller than 13000 ft minus 30 minutes 3) in no case less than 30 minutes for aeroplanes certificated to fly up to 25000 ft 4) in no case less than 2 hours for aeroplanes certificated to fly over 25000 ft  The combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which part of the Operations Manual would you find information regarding flight planning?",
    "feedback": "Part B"
  },
  {
    "question": "Can an Operator use the MMEL instead of the MEL?",
    "feedback": "Yes, if the arrangement is approved by the Competent Authority"
  },
  {
    "question": "If an aircraft has a maximum seating configuration of less than 200 but more than 9, a crash axe or crowbar must be carried:",
    "feedback": "one on the flight deck only"
  },
  {
    "question": "You have recently passed your initial training and line check for an operator and it is only your sixth flight as an inexperienced pilot. During the briefing, you note that the captain you are scheduled to fly with has also recently passed the command upgrade and it is only his/her third flight. Is it allowed to fly together?",
    "feedback": "No, there are too many inexperienced flight crew"
  },
  {
    "question": "During an aircraft de-icing/anti-icing procedure:",
    "feedback": "the anti-icing fluid is applied without heating and the de-icing fluid is applied hot."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is flying along airway T16 within the NAT HLA and is communicating with Shanwick Oceanic control using CPDLC. When passing position GONAN, the CPDLC connection is automatically transferred to Santa Maria Oceanic control. The pilot ....",
    "feedback": "is then required to establish contact with Santa Maria Oceanic control using HF radio in the 2.8 MHz to 18 MHz frequency band"
  },
  {
    "question": "The fire extinguisher types which may be used on class B fires are:\n1 - H2O\n2 - CO2\n3 - dry-chemical\n4 - halogen\n\nWhich of the following combinations contains all of the correct statements?",
    "feedback": "2 - 3 - 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "For aircraft certified before 1 April 1998, cockpit voice recorder must keep the conversations and sound alarms recorded during the last :",
    "feedback": "30 minutes of operation."
  },
  {
    "question": "Following an act of unlawful interference on board an aircraft, the commander has to submit a report to (the):",
    "feedback": "competent authority and shall inform the designated local authority"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, without ETOPS approval, the maximum distance from an adequate aerodrome for two-engined aeroplanes in Performance Class A, with a maximum take-off mass of 45360 kg or more, is the distance flown in ... minutes at the one-engine inoperative cruise speed.",
    "feedback": "60"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the certification flight tests regarding fuel jettisoning it must be shown that:\n\n1) Fuel jettisoning system and its operation are free from fire hazard\n2) The fuel discharges clear of any part of the aeroplane\n3) Fuel fumes do not enter any part of the aeroplane\n4) The jettisoning operation does not adversely affect the controllability of the aeroplane\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The content of the dangerous goods transport document is specified in the:",
    "feedback": "Technical Instructions"
  },
  {
    "question": "The holdover time of an anti-icing procedure, for a given ambient temperature, will be longest in weather conditions of:",
    "feedback": "frost"
  },
  {
    "question": "A four-jet aircraft must be equipped with an in-flight fuel jettisoning system in order to reduce the aircraft weight in an emergency :",
    "feedback": "unless it is capable of meeting the climb requirements : 2.7% in approach configuration with 1 engine inoperative and 3.2% in landing configuration with all engines operative"
  },
  {
    "question": "When considering lateral navigation requirements in NAT HLA, which of the following may grant RNP 10 and RNP 4 aircraft approvals?",
    "feedback": "The State of Registry"
  },
  {
    "question": "In calm wind conditions, an aircraft at take-off creates tip vortices that:",
    "feedback": "separate outwards on each side of the runway"
  },
  {
    "question": "As a flight crew member, you are to report for a period of airport standby. According to the OPS regulations, when does the airport standby period commence?",
    "feedback": "from reporting at the reporting point"
  },
  {
    "question": "The number of hand fire extinguishers which have to be installed in the passenger cabin according to  OPS depends on the approved number of:",
    "feedback": "seats in the cabin"
  },
  {
    "question": "After landing, in case of high temperature of the brakes you:",
    "feedback": "release the parking brake and you approach the wheels either from aft or fore."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft having undergone an anti-icing procedure must be free of anti-icing fluid the latest when :",
    "feedback": "it is rotating (before lifting-off)."
  },
  {
    "question": "After landing heavy and fast, an engineer should approach the landing gear from:",
    "feedback": "the front or rear"
  },
  {
    "question": "To conduct a special VFR flight, the minimum visibility required by EASA AIR OPS is:",
    "feedback": "1500 metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "On landing on an isolated field, the captain of a turbojet engined aircraft must mandatorily have a minimum quantity of fuel and lubricant sufficient for flying during :",
    "feedback": "2 hours with normal cruising consumption"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an aeroplane with a tyre pressure of 12 bars, there is a risk of dynamic hydroplaning as soon as the:",
    "feedback": "speed is greater than 119 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "In icing conditions, if you have exceeded the holdover time, the correct procedure is to:",
    "feedback": "de-ice again the aircraft, then apply anti-icing fluid"
  },
  {
    "question": "Dynamic hydroplaning is a condition that can occur when aircraft ......",
    "feedback": "land on a surface with standing water deeper than the tread depth of the tyres"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, the operator must ensure that the mass and balance documentation of a flight is stored for a minimum period of:",
    "feedback": "3 months"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to ICAO DOC 8168, a noise abatement departure procedure is not to be initiated at less than:",
    "feedback": "800 ft above aerodrome elevation"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are flying over a small bird sanctuary. Choose the correct statement with regards to a bird strike risk:",
    "feedback": "Small birds can cause severe damage"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS 1, what is the planning minima for a destination alternate with a CAT I approach available?",
    "feedback": "Non-precision minima (RVR and the ceiling at or above MDH)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to a precautionary landing:",
    "feedback": "The landing site will be at the earliest opportunity"
  },
  {
    "question": "The North Atlantic airspace is regulated according to :",
    "feedback": "the ICAO document 7030 (additional regional procedures)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given the information, select the lowest required weather conditions for the aerodrome to be used as an ETOPS enroute alternate aerodrome with the following approaches available:\nApproach type: ILS CAT I (DH 240 feet, RVR/visibility 550 metres)Approach type: LOC DME (MDH 420 feet, RVR/visibility 1200 metres)",
    "feedback": "Ceiling 440 feet and visibility 1350 metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the cross-check before entering NAT HLA airspace, what is the limitation on the difference between the two primary altimeters?",
    "feedback": "+ / - 200 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight, the Senior Cabin Crew Member informs the flight crew that a passenger is using a Portable Electronic Device PED (a satellite phone) which could adversely affect the aircraft electronic systems. Which option is correct?",
    "feedback": "In accordance with the operator's procedures, the commander may require the PED to be switched off"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, for aeroplanes intended to be operated at pressure altitude above 25000 ft, the total number of oxygen dispensing units shall exceed the number of:",
    "feedback": "seats by 10%"
  },
  {
    "question": "A crate with the label shown is about to be loaded in an aircraft. The Dangerous Goods label is slightly damaged. According to the orange label, the box must be loaded....",
    "feedback": "in cargo aircraft only"
  },
  {
    "question": "One shall not initiate any flight made in accordance with instrument flight rules unless the available information indicates that the conditions at the aerodrome of predicted destination or, at an aerodrome of alternative destination, are: (Annex 6, Part I)",
    "feedback": "At the predicted time of arrival equal to or better than the minimum conditions required for aerodrome use."
  },
  {
    "question": "If both precision navigation systems of an aircraft are unserviceable during a flight in MNPS airspace, and if you cannot establish communication with the air traffic control, you :",
    "feedback": "take an intermediate flight level"
  },
  {
    "question": "The correct definition of a safe forced landing is:",
    "feedback": "an inevitable landing on land or sea from which one may reasonably expect no injuries on board or on the surface"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is working for an Operator that has only one aircraft type and variant in their fleet. The Operator is introducting a new aircraft that is considered a common type with the existing fleet, but a different variant to the existing aircraft. \nAccording to AMC1 ORO.FC.125, in order to operate on both variants, the pilot....",
    "feedback": "must complete differences training containing both theoretical and practical training"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Master Minimum Equipment List (MMEL) defines the equipment on which certain in-flight failures can be allowed and the conditions under which this allowance can be accepted. This MMEL is drawn up by :",
    "feedback": "the manufacturer and approved by the certification authority"
  },
  {
    "question": "Bird hazards are likely to be encountered in some of the following areas:\n1) built up area2) trees and shrubs3) coastal area4) ploughed field5) noisy environment6) rubbish tips and short grass\nWhich of the following combinations is correct?",
    "feedback": "3, 4, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\nSNOWTAM 0183A) ESSAB) 01230720C) 01LF) 5/5/5G) 02/02/02H) 4/3/3N) 25/MEDIUM 02 MM CONTAMINATION 50 PERCENT\nC) 01RF) 5/5/5G) 01/02/02H) 5/5/4N) 25/MEDIUM 02 MM CONTAMINATION 50 PERCENT\nC) 08F) 6/6/5G) 01/01/01H) 4/4/4N) 25/MEDIUM 01MM CONTAMINATION 25 PERCENT\nR) 25/POOR 08MM CONTAMINATION 100 PERCENTT) DE ICING FLUIDS ON RWY 01L 01R AND 08\nDeposits of slush are reported for;",
    "feedback": "Runway 08"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there is a fire in the cargo compartment in the lower half of the fuselage, what is your action?",
    "feedback": "Turn off the ventilation"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft which experiencies a headwind of 40 kt while making its way towards the centre of a microburst may expect, when crossing the microburst,  to face a windshear of :",
    "feedback": "80 kt."
  },
  {
    "question": "How is the uncleared part of a contaminated runway reported in a SNOWTAM?",
    "feedback": "In plain language at item T (the final paragraph) of a SNOWTAM"
  },
  {
    "question": "ICAO Annex 18 is a document dealing with:",
    "feedback": "the safety of the air transport of dangerous goods"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a landing approach, the aircraft is subjected to windshear with an increasing tail wind. In the absence of a pilot action, the aircraft :\n\n1- flies above the glide path\n2- flies below the gilde path\n3- has an increasing true airspeed\n4- has a decreasing true airspeed\n\nThe combination of correct statements is :",
    "feedback": "2,4."
  },
  {
    "question": "Reference shall be made to the Minimum Equipment List (MEL) for equipment found unserviceable at any time:",
    "feedback": "prior to the flight time stage"
  },
  {
    "question": "Just after take-off an aircraft encounters a microburst situated directly ahead. The initial indications will be:\n\n1) an increase in head wind\n2) an increase in tail wind\n3) better climb performance\n4) a decrease in climb gradient\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following requirements should be met when planning a flight in icing conditions?",
    "feedback": "The aircraft shall be equipped with approved ice protection systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "The minimum requirements for Supplemental Oxygen to be supplied in pressurised aeroplanes during and following an emergency descent are that for pilots it shall be available for the entire flight time that the cabin pressure altitude exceeds a minimum of X feet. \n\nThat minimum of X feet is :",
    "feedback": "13000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "A hijacker has just entered the flight crew compartment, destroying all radio equipment. What is the correct action by the crew?",
    "feedback": "Try to contact ATC via CPDLC"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following options correctly states the difference in operation of carbon and steel brakes?",
    "feedback": "High speed and long braking for carbon brakes"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, what is the planning minima for a destination alternate with a CAT II approach available?",
    "feedback": "RVR according to CAT I"
  },
  {
    "question": "The operator shall include in the Operations Manual a Minimum Equipment List which shall be approved by the Authority of:",
    "feedback": "the country of the operator"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, on a IFR flight a commander shall not commence takeoff unless the expected weather conditions at the destination and/or required alternate aerodrome(s) are at or above:",
    "feedback": "the planning minima, at the estimated time of arrival."
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, the cockpit voice recorder, when required, must start to record automatically:",
    "feedback": "prior to the aeroplane moving under its own power until the termination of the flight when the aeroplane is no longer capable of moving under its own power"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most common extinguishing agent used in gas turbine engine fire protection systems is:",
    "feedback": "Halon"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which of the following airspaces may VORs be referenced to True North?",
    "feedback": "Canadian Northern Domestic Airspace"
  },
  {
    "question": "ICAO Annex 6 specifies the requirements for equipment to be available in aeroplanes engaged in international commercial operations. What lights must the aircraft be equipped with during the flight?",
    "feedback": "Three navigation lights and two landing lights when the aeroplane is operated at night"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which errors in \"estimates\" minutes shall be reported by aircraft overflying the North Atlantic?",
    "feedback": "3 or more."
  },
  {
    "question": "A water fire extinguisher can be used without restriction for:\n\n1. a paper fire\n2. a hydrocarbon fire\n3. a fabric fire\n4. an electrical fire\n5. a wood fire\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 3, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is overflying a mountainous area when the pilot observes the clouds shown in the figure. Mountain waves are frequently associated with this area. Therefore, a pilot flying in areas where these types of clouds are observed should consider the:",
    "feedback": "Performance of the aeroplane, as the downward component at the back of the waves may be greater than the achievable rate of climb"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, if the flight is to be carried out at FL 290, demonstration concerning oxygen equipment must be completed before:",
    "feedback": "take-off"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is considering the possibility of having to carry out a rejected take-off on a flooded runway and is evaluating the aircraft configuration and the selection of the take-off speeds. From the given information, choose the lowest possible flap setting that would avoid dynamic hydroplaning in case of a rejected take-off\nTake-off Mass: 70000 kgTyre pressure: 200 psi",
    "feedback": "Flaps 10"
  },
  {
    "question": "In NAT region, a revised estimate should be transmitted to the ATS when the estimated time for the next position has changed by:",
    "feedback": "3 minutes or more"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose the statement which best describes the possible effects of initiating take-off without clearing external aircraft surfaces of ice (except as permitted in the flight manual). The effects of icing ......",
    "feedback": "Are wide-ranging, unpredictable and dependent on the individual aircraft design"
  },
  {
    "question": "When viewed from behind, an aeroplane's vortex circulation is ......",
    "feedback": "outward, upward and around the wing tips"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following may be used to fight a flight deck fire?\n\n1) CO2\n2) Halon\n3) Dry Powder\n4) Water",
    "feedback": "1,2"
  },
  {
    "question": "An automatic toilet fire extinguisher is activated by:",
    "feedback": "heat detection"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following factors should prevent a runway being chosen as the preferential landing runway for noise abatement purposes in visual meteorological condition (VMC) ?",
    "feedback": "It has no ILS or visual approach slope guidance"
  },
  {
    "question": "If there are icing conditions on the ground...",
    "feedback": "you follow the 'clean aircraft concept'"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, when a flight data recorder is required, it must start automatically to record the data:",
    "feedback": "prior to the aircraft being capable of moving under its own power"
  },
  {
    "question": "Your aircraft has just arrived and is on a quick turn-around, during the walkaround you notice ice on the ground and freezing rain on the windhshield, you:",
    "feedback": "Have the aircraft inspected as the flight control surface might be jammed by frozen water residues in the tracks"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot in command:\n\n1) Must comply with ATC instructions immediately.\n2) Is only responsible when airborne.\n3) May deviate in an emergency.\n4) May deviate from complying with rules of the air in order to comply with an ATC instruction.\n5) May request a new clearance if unsatisfied.\n\nThe combination regrouping the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "3, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "Astronomic precession is :",
    "feedback": "existing whether the aircraft is on the ground or flying"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to North Artlantic MNPSA Operations Manual, what is the transponder code to be selected continuously 30 minutes after entry into NAT airspace?",
    "feedback": "Code 2000"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which part of the operations manual would you find information regarding technical procedures of your aircraft?",
    "feedback": "Part A and B"
  },
  {
    "question": "At a high ambient temperature (+ 30° C) and with a relative humidity as low as 40 %, in air free of cloud, fog and precipitation, serious carburettor icing :",
    "feedback": "can occur, but only at a low power setting"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, an operator shall ensure that a pilot does not operate an aeroplane as pilot-in-command unless :",
    "feedback": "he has carried out at least three take-off and three landings as pilot flying in an aeroplane or an approved flight simulator of the type to be used, in the preceding 90 days"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are a newly qualified pilot having recently passed the line check with an established Operator on a multi-pilot aircraft. When arriving in the crew room for the sixth sector/flight with that Operator after training and the line check, you realise that the Commander is also recently qualified and this is only the third sector/flight that he/she will fly with the Operator as Commander.\nWhich statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "A maximum of one inexperienced flight crew member is permitted on any flight and enquiries should be made about this crew composition"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is intended to be operated at FL 370. In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, the number of cabin oxygen masks (dispensing units) required is at least:",
    "feedback": "110% of the seating capacity"
  },
  {
    "question": "The information to consider for a standard non precision approach is:\n\n1 - the horizontal visibility\n2 - the ceiling\n3 - the minimum descending altitude (MDA)\n4 - the decision altitude (DA)\n\nWhich of the following combinations contains all of the correct statements?",
    "feedback": "1 - 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Collect snow and forming it into a ball where it keeps its shape as a snowball. This refers to:",
    "feedback": "wet snow"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to ICAO Annex 6, a flight data analysis programme shall contain adequate safeguards to protect the (1) .... in accordance with (2) .... .",
    "feedback": "(1) source(s), (2) ICAO Annex 19"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming contaminated runway conditions, if an aeroplane's mainwheel tyre pressure is 206 psi., the approximate speed above which dynamic hydroplaning may occur is :",
    "feedback": "129 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "The greatest wake turbulence occurs when the generating aircraft is :",
    "feedback": "Large, heavy, at low speed in clean configuration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Following an explosive decompression, if you are using an oxygen diluter demand system, the regulator controls the amount of air that is mixed with pure oxygen when the supply selector is at the \"normal\" position. \n\nAt what approximate altitude will the regulator supply to the mask become pure oxygen only ?",
    "feedback": "32000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "When taking-off behind a wide-body aircraft, with wind coming from the right side, you adopt a path, whenever possible :",
    "feedback": "distinct from the preceding airplane, by remaining on the right of and above its path."
  },
  {
    "question": "After a commercial passenger flight, the flight crew awaits their luggage at the baggage carousel. Their hold luggage is delivered last, when all the passengers have already left. The flight crew notices that there is a piece of luggage remaining on the carousel which has not been claimed. According to ICAO Annex 17 and for security reasons, the definition of such baggage would be:",
    "feedback": "Unidentified baggage"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aerodrome operating minima for a VOR/DME approach are:  MDH = 360 ft Required RVR = 1500 metres Reported RVR = 1800 metres  According to EASA AIR OPS, the pilot may continue the final approach:",
    "feedback": "regardless of the ceiling reported"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an aeroplane with a tyre pressure of 10 bars, there is a risk of dynamic hydroplaning as soon as the:",
    "feedback": "speed is greater than 108 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which chapter (part) of the Operations Manual would you find information on general operational policies and procedures?",
    "feedback": "Part A"
  },
  {
    "question": "The validity period of a westbound organised track system in MNPS airspace is normally, at 30°W, between:",
    "feedback": "1130 UTC to 1900 UTC"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct when considering a ditching situation?",
    "feedback": "In case of strong winds you will try to land into the wind which may put you in a position slightly across the waves"
  },
  {
    "question": "List the types of de-icing/anti-icing fluids available:",
    "feedback": "Type I, II, III, IV"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, the lowest minima to be used by an operator for circling with a category B aeroplane is a meteorological visibility of:",
    "feedback": "1600 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "A package containing Lithium-Ion Batteries is to be transported by aircraft. In the Technical Instructions (ICAO DOC 9284) you see a number \"3480\" listed in column 2. What does the number represent?",
    "feedback": "The item's UN number"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which part of the OPS manual would you find information regarding mass and balance?",
    "feedback": "Part A & B"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS,  what minimum navigation equipment is required for operations under IFR, or under VFR over routes not navigated by reference to visual landmarks?",
    "feedback": "One VOR receiving system, one ADF system, one DME"
  },
  {
    "question": "A flight crew has been on standby duty for 4 hours at an airport. How many hours of duty time will this standby time count as?",
    "feedback": "4 hours, as airport standby counts in full as duty time"
  },
  {
    "question": "When looking for a bomb on board an aircraft, what is to be used as the primary guideline?",
    "feedback": "A search procedure checklist"
  },
  {
    "question": "Fire fighting in the toilets must be performed with:",
    "feedback": "all available extinguishers simultaneously."
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, for two-engined aeroplanes in Performance Class B or C without an ETOPS approval, the maximum distance from an adequate aerodrome is the distance flown in ...(i)... minutes at the one-engine inoperative cruise speed, or ...(ii)... nautical miles, whichever is less.",
    "feedback": "(i) 120 (ii) 300"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is planning a flight to an airfield which is known to have a much higher concentration of birds than normal. This could present a danger to aircraft operation. What is the most probable source where the pilot can get information?",
    "feedback": "Via a NOTAM"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS (Aerodrome Operating Minima), an operator must ensure that the MDH for an ILS approach without the glidepath (LLZ only) is not lower than:",
    "feedback": "250 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The standard lateral separation minima to be maintained between aircraft flying in NAT MNPS airspace is :",
    "feedback": "60 NM."
  },
  {
    "question": "You are performing the last flight of the day, which is a humanitarian aid mission with only cargo on board. What is true regarding the security check?",
    "feedback": "This must be done before departure to avoid the risk of unlawful interference"
  },
  {
    "question": "After de-icing/anti-icing still in freezing conditions, how should you position the aircraft?",
    "feedback": "In neither"
  },
  {
    "question": "A fire in the toilet waste bin is extinguished with:",
    "feedback": "BCF"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, for aeroplanes intended to be operated at pressure altitude of 39000 ft, the total number of oxygen dispensing units and outlets shall exceed",
    "feedback": "the number of seats by at least 10%"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a commercial air transport flight, when carrying special categories of passengers (SCPs), such as persons with reduced mobility (PRMs), ....",
    "feedback": "the commander must be notified"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a conventional approach, the Minimum Descent Height (MDH) is referred to the runway threshold altitude and not to the aerodrome altitude if the runway threshold is at more than :",
    "feedback": "2 m (7 ft) below the aerodrome altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "Following a heavy mass landing on a short runway, attention should be paid to the:",
    "feedback": "temperature of the brakes"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the winter an aircraft is parked overnight prior to an early morning departure. The crew notice a slight glistening ice deposit on top of the wings or blades which appears translucent. Under these conditions:",
    "feedback": "the aircraft should be sprayed with de-icing fluid of the correct type."
  },
  {
    "question": "The main feature of BCF fire extinguishers is that they:",
    "feedback": "act as flame inhibitors by absorbing the air's oxygen."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the statements below are correct regarding the effects of wind shear on take-off reference speeds?\n1) The take-off should be rejected if unacceptable airspeed variations occur below V12) The take-off should be continued after V1 has been reached, regardless of wind shear conditions3) Wind shear does not affect the take-off decision speed4) In severe wind shear encounters, under no circumstances should a rotation be started before VR is reached (for most transport category aircraft types)",
    "feedback": "1, 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a night flight, an observer located in the cockpit, seeing an aircraft coming from the front right, will first see the :",
    "feedback": "red steady light"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft operating within MNPS airspace is unable to continue flight in accordance with its air traffic control clearance, but is able to maintain its assigned level, and due to a total loss of communications capability, cannot obtain a revised clearance from ATC. The aircraft should offset from the assigned route by 15 NM and climb or descend 500 ft, if:",
    "feedback": "below FL 410"
  },
  {
    "question": "The validity period of a line check shall be 12 calendar months counted from ....",
    "feedback": "the end of the month when the check was taken"
  },
  {
    "question": "Due to a cabin pressurization defect the maximum differential pressure is limited to 2 psi. Assuming you don't want the cabin altitude being greater than 10000 feet, the maximum achievable flight altitude is approximately:",
    "feedback": "15100 ft."
  },
  {
    "question": "When crossing the Intertropical Convergence Zone (ITCZ), where there are very large, active clouds, the pilot flying should be aware that ......",
    "feedback": "ice may form at the pitot tubes and static ports, giving false airspeed indications"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS an aeroplane whose maximum approved passenger seating configuration is greater than 60 seats must be equipped (including flight deck) with at least:",
    "feedback": "3 HALON 1211 fire extinguishers or equivalent"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to Annex 6 Part I, \"flight time\" is defined as the total time from the moment an aeroplane:",
    "feedback": "first moves for the purpose of taking off until the moment it finally comes to rest at the end of the flight"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which part of the Operations Manual would you find information regarding search and rescue procedures?",
    "feedback": "Part A"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a microburst downdrafts in the order of 3000 to 4000 ft/min can produce vector changes in horizontal wind of:",
    "feedback": "60 to 80 kts."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the dispersal time for wake turbulence from a wide-bodied aircraft?",
    "feedback": "3 minutes."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft airworthiness certificate states a maximum of eight occupants (including pilot).\nThe pilot has a passenger load of six adults and two children (5 and 6 years old).\nThe boarding of all passengers is:",
    "feedback": "forbidden."
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, which of the following are included in the Aerodrome Operating Minima for a non-precision approach?\n\n1) the required RVR\n2) the ceiling\n3) the minimum descent height (MDH)\n4) the decision height (DH)\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a long-range four-jet aircraft in cruising flight, the optimum altitude and the lock-on altitude increase. The most cost-effective flight plan will consist of chosing cruising levels which increase during the flight in order to fly :",
    "feedback": "about the optimum altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Minimum Equipment List (MEL) is be established by:",
    "feedback": "the aircraft operator and approved by the authority"
  },
  {
    "question": "Two aeroplanes from two different Operators are flying the same route. Throughout the flight, the aeroplane behind experiences occasional wake vortices from the aeroplane ahead. When will the aircraft flying behind experience the stongest wake turbulence?\nWhen the aeroplane in front is flying at:",
    "feedback": "Its minimum clean speed after departure as this is when the aeroplane is at its heaviest"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under what circumstances may an operator introduce alternative procedures to those prescribed in EASA AIR OPS Subpart M (Maintenance)?",
    "feedback": "When needed and when an equivalent safety case has first been approved by the Authority and supported by JAA Member Authorities"
  },
  {
    "question": "The EASA OPS aeroplane and helicopter are based on :",
    "feedback": "ICAO Appendix 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, \"pre-flight inspection\" is the inspection carried out:",
    "feedback": "before flight to ensure that the aircraft is fit for the intended flight. It does not include defect rectification."
  },
  {
    "question": "A crew is flying from New York to Tokyo on a route that takes them close to the magnetic North Pole. While flying in the Canadian Northern Domestic Airspace, one IRS fails and a crew member wants to check the position of the aircraft using a navigation aid.\nWhich of the following should the crew member consider in this situation?",
    "feedback": "The VORs within this area may be orientated with reference to True North, rather than Magnetic North"
  },
  {
    "question": "During cruise you encounter an engine fire indication. What is your first action?",
    "feedback": "You follow the engine shut down procedures in Operations Manual Part B"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is applicable when considering the loading of radioactive materials?",
    "feedback": "These materials should be loaded in a way that limits the exposure of persons to radiation"
  },
  {
    "question": "In case of a fire due to the heating of the brakes, you fight the fire using:\n\n1. a dry powder fire extinguisher\n2. a water spray atomizer\n3. a water fire-extinguisher\n4. a CO2 fire-extinguisher to the maximum\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is flying an aircraft in the NAT HLA, along the eastbound Organised Track System (OTS) and intends to follow TOS Track \"V\" for its entire length. The pilot may plan to cruise at:",
    "feedback": "FL320"
  },
  {
    "question": "The operator shall include in the operations manual a Minimum Equipment List which shall be approved by the Authority of : (Annex 6, Part I)",
    "feedback": "the country of the operator."
  },
  {
    "question": "In which part of the Operations Manual would you find information regarding the companies fuel policy?",
    "feedback": "Part A"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct about the management of aeronautical databases?",
    "feedback": "The operator shall ensure the timely distribution and insertion of current and unaltered aeronautical databases to all aircraft that require them"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is a possible immediate physiological effect of an explosive decompression in an extreme case?",
    "feedback": "Ruptured ear drums"
  },
  {
    "question": "Define \"frost\":",
    "feedback": "A deposit of ice, respectively cystallized water vapour, having a crystalline appearance, generally assuming the form of scales, needles or fans"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the definition of a minimum time route?",
    "feedback": "Shortest time between destination and departure adhering to ATC restrictions"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot is taxiing out for take-off on a very hot day and his/her aircraft is equipped with carbon brakes. The pilot is aware that it is going to be a long taxi and wants to maximise the brakes' ability to absorb energy in case of a rejected take-off. To control the taxi speed, he/she decides to use:",
    "feedback": "Firm brake applications, as carbon-brake wear is determined by the number of times the brakes are applied"
  },
  {
    "question": "The primary objective of each Contracting State as regards safeguarding against acts of unlawful interference with civil aviation is the safety of which of the following?\n1) Passengers2) Crew3) The aircraft4) Ground personnel5) The general public6) Aerodrome buildings",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 4, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying behind a large aircraft to take pictures. It is slightly below and outboard of the wing of the preceding aircraft. What will be most likely happen due to wake turbulence?",
    "feedback": "It will roll towards the preceding aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, an operator shall not operate an aircraft in expected or actual icing conditions unless:",
    "feedback": "the aircraft is certified and equipped to operate in icing conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "Following a heavy mass landing on a short runway, you should check the :",
    "feedback": "temperature of the brakes."
  },
  {
    "question": "A analysis of the bird strikes shows that the highest risk is encountered in a layer from :",
    "feedback": "from 0 to 150 m."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is configured for seating 61 to 200 passengers. What is the requirement for hand held fire extinguishers?",
    "feedback": "3 conveniently located in the passenger compartment"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following fire extinguisher types can be used for the given classes of fire?",
    "feedback": "Halon/BCF for classes A, B, and C"
  },
  {
    "question": "With regard to the management of aeronautical databases, to whom shall the Operator report erroneous, inconsistent, or missing data that might be reasonably expected to constitute a hazard to flight?",
    "feedback": "The data provider"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:\n\ng = the longitude difference\nLm = the average latitude\nLo = the latitude of the tangent\n\nThe transport precession is equal to:",
    "feedback": "g x sin Lm"
  },
  {
    "question": "Aeroplanes having a maximum approved seating capacity between 61 and 200 passengers will require the following number of megaphones on the passenger deck:",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS and if required, the number of life rafts to be carried on board an aeroplane must allow the transportation of the entire aeroplane occupants:",
    "feedback": "in the case of a loss of one raft of the largest rated capability"
  },
  {
    "question": "A category I precision approach (CAT I) has :",
    "feedback": "a decision height equal to at least 200 ft."
  },
  {
    "question": "What items for use in fire fighting would you expect to see close to a fire extinguisher?",
    "feedback": "all of the above"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is correct concerning a take-off from a contaminated runway?",
    "feedback": "In general the performance data for take-off has been determined by means of calculation and has not been verified by flight tests"
  },
  {
    "question": "The permanent approval for the transport of dangerous goods is specified in the:",
    "feedback": "Air Operator Certificate"
  },
  {
    "question": "The validity period of a \"certificate of airworthiness\" varies with the conditions under which the aircraft is maintained.\nIf the maintenance is carried out according to an approved programme and done in a maintenance shop approved by the Minister of Civil Aviation, the validity period is:",
    "feedback": "three years."
  },
  {
    "question": "Who must finally determine that the load and its distribution is such that the mass and balance limits of the aircraft are not exceeded and confirm their acceptance by countersigning the mass and balance documentation?",
    "feedback": "The commander"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, for a non-pressurised aircraft, the supplemental oxygen is:",
    "feedback": "required to operate at pressure altitudes above 10000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft on a bi-directional route in the NAT region is experiencing turbulence from an aircraft ahead and above. According to the Strategic Lateral Offset Procedure (SLOP), can the pilot of the affected aircraft offset to reduce the effects of this wake turbulence, and if yes, then how?",
    "feedback": "Offset right of the cleared track centre-line"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, the Minimum Equipment List of an aircraft is to be found in the:",
    "feedback": "Operations Manual"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight to Europe, planned in MNPS (Minimum Navigation Performance Specification) airspace, you expect to cross the 30°W meridian at 11H00 UTC ; you will then normally be :",
    "feedback": "out of the organized flight track system."
  },
  {
    "question": "How should a fire in a laptop computer with a lithium-ion battery in the passenger cabin be dealt with?",
    "feedback": "Use an appropriate hand held fire extinguisher"
  },
  {
    "question": "In final approach, you encounter a strong rear wind gust or strong down wind which forces you to go around. You\n\n1- maintain the same aircraft configuration (gear and flaps)\n2- reduce the drags (gear and flaps)\n3- gradually increase the attitude up to triggering of stick shaker\n4- avoid excessive attitude change\n\nThe combination of correct statements is :",
    "feedback": "1,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "ICAO Annex 6 describes the content associated with the completion of a maintenance release. The purpose of the maintenance release for an aircraft is ....",
    "feedback": "to confirm that any maintenance work conducted on an aircraft has been completed satisfactorily in accordance with approved data and procedures"
  },
  {
    "question": "Due to a cabin pressurisation defect the maximum differential pressure is limited to 2 psi. Assuming the oxygen masks will be deployed at 14000 feet, the maximum achievable flight altitude is approximately :",
    "feedback": "20750 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what AIP section would you find information about bird migration?",
    "feedback": "ENR"
  },
  {
    "question": "The tyre pressure of an aircraft main landing gear is 10,8 bars. There is a risk of hydroplaning as soon as the speed reaches:",
    "feedback": "113 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "A blocked pitot head with a clear static source causes the airspeed indicator to:",
    "feedback": "react like an altimeter"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, planning minima for a destination aerodrome with an applicable precision approach procedure is:",
    "feedback": "RVR/visibility specified in accordance with EASA OPS Aerodrome Operating Minima"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight, some passengers report an unusual petroleum-like smell in the cabin and some liquid leaking from a bag. It seems that the bag is carrying several containers of lighter fuel packed in a clear, sealable bag in accordance with the security regulations regarding the volume of liquids passengers can generally bring on board as part of the hand luggage.\nWhat must the captain do?",
    "feedback": "Report the event as an occurrence involving undeclared dangerous goods"
  },
  {
    "question": "On an alternate field, the captain of turbojet engined aircraft must mandatorily have a quantity of fuel and lubricant sufficient for flying during :",
    "feedback": "30 minutes at holding flight speed and 1500 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "One of the primary factors causing dynamic hydroplaning is:",
    "feedback": "the depth of the standing water on the runway."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which parameter will change first, when penetrating a horizontal windshear?",
    "feedback": "Indicated airspeed"
  },
  {
    "question": "During an explosive decompression at flight level 370 (FL 370), your first action will be :",
    "feedback": "to put on the oxygen mask"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements correctly describes the operation of an engine fire handle?",
    "feedback": "Pulling the handle cuts off the fuel, twisting it fires the extinguisher"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight to Europe, planned in MNPS (Minimum Navigation Performance Specification) airspace, you expect to cross the 30°W meridian at 00H30 UTC ; you will then normally be ;",
    "feedback": "out of the organized flight track system"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which option correctly lists the wind conditions that can be dangerous as regards wake turbulence, bei either keeping the wake turbulence on the runway or causing it to drift to another runway?",
    "feedback": "Calm wind, light cross wind, or light tail wind"
  },
  {
    "question": "If cabin altitude increases during level flight, the differential pressure :",
    "feedback": "decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "When establishing an instrument approach procedure, 5 aircraft categories according to their speed at the threshold (Vat) are established. This speed is equal to the stalling speed in the landing configuration at the maximum certified landing weight multiplied by a factor of:",
    "feedback": "1.3"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, an aeroplane whose maximum approved passenger seating configuration is 31 to 60 seats must be equipped with at least:",
    "feedback": "2 hand fire extinguishers conveniently located in the passenger compartment"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a landing approach, the aircraft is subjected to windshear with an increasing head wind.In the absence of a pilot action, the aircraft :\n\n1- flies above the glide path\n2- flies below theglide path\n3- has an increasing true airspeed\n4- has a decreasing true airspeed\n\nThe combination of correct statements is :",
    "feedback": "1,3."
  },
  {
    "question": "The wake turbulence is greater when the aircraft has a :",
    "feedback": "high weight and low speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with AIR OPS, the noise abatement procedures specified by the operator should be:",
    "feedback": "the same for all airports for the same airplane type"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, what is the planning minima for a destination aerodrome, if it is equipped with a non-precision approach only?",
    "feedback": "RVR/visibility specified in accordance with EASA AIR OPS, and the ceiling at or above MDH"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the recommended \"noise abatement take-off and climb procedure NADP 1\" established  in ICAO, DOC 8168 Volume I part V, Chapter 3, acceleration to en-route climb speed has to be done as soon as the aircraft reaches :",
    "feedback": "3 000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft  flying above flight level 410 on MNPS Airspace is unable to continue flight in accordance with its air traffic control clearance (degradation of navigational performance requirements, mechanics troubles... etc), but is able to maintain its assigned level, and due  to a total loss of communications capability, could not obtain a revised clearance from ATC. The aircraft should leave its assigned route or track by turning 90° (90 degrees) to the right of left whenever this is possible, and the subsequent action will be, turn to acquire and maintain in either direction track laterally separated by 30 NM from its assigned route and :",
    "feedback": "climb or descend 1 000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "A check on the operation of the SELCAL equipment during a transatlantic flight using the OTS (Organised Track System) must be done :",
    "feedback": "At or prior entering the NAT region."
  },
  {
    "question": "For an aeroplane with a tyre pressure of 14 bars, there is a risk of dynamic hydroplaning as soon as the:",
    "feedback": "speed is greater than 129 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose the correct statement if icing conditions are encountered:",
    "feedback": "a decrease of lift by 30%"
  },
  {
    "question": "The Pilot-in-Command has just rejected a take-off in a transport category aircraft close to its maximum take-off mass. The rejection was made at approximately 60 knots indicated airspeed due to a blocked runway. Prior to attempting another take-off, as regards to the aircraft tyres and brakes, what should the flight crew consider?",
    "feedback": "Calculate and wait for the expiry of brake cooling time before attempting a subsequent take-off"
  },
  {
    "question": "The chart is a South polar stereographic projection of the Antarctic regions. A grid, printed over it, its aligned with meridian 180°, the grid North in the direction of the geographic North (non standard grid). The grid course followed by the aircraft is Rg=280°, the position is 80°S 100°E. The true course followed at this moment is :",
    "feedback": "000°."
  },
  {
    "question": "With regard to ICAO Annex 18, when offering dangerous goods for transportation by air, who initially is responsible for compliance with the regulations?",
    "feedback": "The shipper"
  },
  {
    "question": "The wake turbulence caused by an aircraft is mainly the result of:\n\n1. An aerodynamical effect (wing tip vortices).\n2. The engines action (propellers rotation or engine gas exhausts).\n3. The importance of the drag devices (size of the landing gear, of the flaps, etc.).\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1."
  },
  {
    "question": "A senior cabin crew member notices traces of smoke in the passenger cabin but can not positively identify its source of origin. The aircraft commander is notified and after the relevant abnormal checklist has been completed, his/her action will normally be to:",
    "feedback": "divert to the nearest aerodrome"
  },
  {
    "question": "An extract from the European Regulation on Air Operations and the applicable AMC and GM is shown. An operator assigns a pilot to fly as single pilot of a light twin-engined aeroplane on a local flight in the area of the Alps with paying passengers. All flights are conducted during daytime and according to VFR. Which statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "There are no requirements for recency but the area within which the operation is conducted may have specific national requirements"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, for a non-pressurised aircraft, all required cabin crew members shall be supplied with supplemental oxygen during:",
    "feedback": "the entire flight time at pressure altitudes above 13000 ft and for any period exceeding 30 minutes at pressure altitudes above 10000 ft but not exceeding 13000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The file kept by an employer on its flight crews records:  1 - the training 2 - the test results 3 - a log of flying hours 4 - a summary of the training by reference period  Which of the following combinations contains all of the correct answers?",
    "feedback": "1 - 2 - 3 - 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "When a course is plotted at minimum time route, one passes from the air isochrone to the corresponding ground isochrone by applying to point K (original spot) a vector KK' which is equal to:",
    "feedback": "mean wind from the preceding ground isochrone."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, the pre-flight fuel calculation for a VFR flight for aeroplanes with reciprocating engines must include a final reserve to fly for:",
    "feedback": "45 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "The regulations for transportation of dangerous goods are contained in:",
    "feedback": "ICAO Annex 18 and ICAO DOC 9284"
  },
  {
    "question": "A jet aircraft is certified for the carriage of 120 passengers. 42 passengers are on board and the expected flight level on route Paris-Algers is FL 330. The first aid oxygen to be on board at departure shall provide breathing supply for a least:",
    "feedback": "1 passenger for the entire flight after cabin depressurization at a cabin altitude of more than 8000 feet."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to Annex 6, what is the definition of Required Navigation Performance (RNP)?",
    "feedback": "A statement of the navigation performance necessary for operation within a defined airspace"
  },
  {
    "question": "A dry chemical type fire extinguisher could be used to fight the fire of:\n\n1) paper, fabric, carpet\n2) flammable liquids\n3) electrical equipment\n4) metals, flammable gases, chemicals\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, where dangerous goods are carried on a flight which takes place wholly or partly outside the territory of a State, which language(s) must be used on the transport document in addition to any other language?",
    "feedback": "English"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the reason for dumping fuel during an emergency after take-off?",
    "feedback": "To get below maximum landing mass (MLM)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The captain is asked by the authority to present the documents of the airplane. He",
    "feedback": "must do so, within a reasonable period of time."
  },
  {
    "question": "The anti-icing fluid protecting film can wear off and reduce the holdover time considerably:",
    "feedback": "during strong winds or as a result of the other aircraft engines jet wash."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is flying from Thessaloniki/Makedonia (LGTS) to Kavala/Megas Alexandros (LGKV) within Greece. Which of the following documents/publications must the Commander check, in order to be familiar with any published Noise Abatement Departure Procedures (NADP) for the departure aerodrome?",
    "feedback": "Greek AIP/LGTS-AD2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Water fire extinguisher with a directed spray can be used on:",
    "feedback": "Solid fires"
  },
  {
    "question": "Noise abatement procedure type 1 (NADP 1) is used for noise reduction:",
    "feedback": "near the airfield"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the event of a contingency which required an en-route diversion to an alternate aerodrome across the direction of the prevailing \"NAT\" traffic flow and if prior ATC clearance cannot be obtained an aircraft able to maintain its assigned flight level should:",
    "feedback": "If at FL410, climb 1000 ft or descend 500 ft, while turning towards the alternate aerodrome."
  },
  {
    "question": "On which of the following types of fire should a Halon fire extinguisher preferably be used?",
    "feedback": "hydrocarbon"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the reason for selecting a suitable take-off alternate aerodrome?",
    "feedback": "To ensure a safe landing can be made in case of emergency after take-off when the departure aerodrome can not be used due to performance or meteorological reasons"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight, the chief steward informs the crew that a passenger is using a portable device suspected to disturb the aircraft electronic systems. The captain:",
    "feedback": "must not authorize any person to use such a device on board."
  },
  {
    "question": "Selecting an alternate aerodrome the runway of this facility must be sufficiently long to allow a full stop landing from 50 ft above the threshold (jet type aircraft, dry runway) within:",
    "feedback": "60% of the landing distance available."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following operational scenario indicates understanding of the \"Clean Aircraft Concept\" with respect to aircraft de-/anti-icing operations as determined by ICAO?",
    "feedback": "After completion of ground de-/anti-icing, the Pilot in Command requests a close-up visual inspection of the horizontal stabiliser upper surface, which is not visible from the ground"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is part of the \"security restricted area\"?",
    "feedback": "The airside catering and aircraft cleaning premises"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, for a pressurised aeroplane, the minimum requirement for supplemental oxygen needed to supply 100% of the passengers following a cabin pressurisation failure, is:",
    "feedback": "the entire flight time where the cabin pressure altitude exceeds 15000 ft, but in no case less than 10 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, the selection of a destination alternate is not required when:",
    "feedback": "the destination is isolated and no adequate destination alternate exists"
  },
  {
    "question": "During cruise, the senior cabin crew member notifies the flight crew that two armed men are threatening the cabin crew and the passengers. Which SSR code must be used by the flight crew in this scenario?",
    "feedback": "7500"
  },
  {
    "question": "A non-pressurised aeroplane which is fitted with 12 passenger seats is intending to perform an IFR flight at night. Is airborne weather radar (AWR) required?",
    "feedback": "Yes, if thunderstorms are expected"
  },
  {
    "question": "For turbo-jet aircraft, in the flight preparation stage, the landing distance at the scheduled destination aerodrome shall be less than the available landing distance multiplied by a factor of :",
    "feedback": "0.6"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where in the Operations Manual can you find information about incident reports of your company if you are acting as a captain under AOC?",
    "feedback": "Part A"
  },
  {
    "question": "Using sample table 10.4.A to determine which Dangerous Goods may be stowed next to each other in an aircraft's cargo compartment.\nWhich statement correctly describes an acceptable loading configuration?",
    "feedback": "One package classified \"4.3\" next to one package classified \"5.1\""
  },
  {
    "question": "How many inexperienced flight crew members may be allowed in any flight crew?",
    "feedback": "A maximum of one"
  },
  {
    "question": "Astronomic precession :",
    "feedback": "causes the gyro axis to spin to the right in the Northern hemisphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following is true related to the clean aircraft concept?",
    "feedback": "If requested by the de-icing staff, the Commander may perform an external check on critical surfaces after de-ice/anti-ice treatment"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, a Category I operation is a precision instrument approach and landing with a decision height (DH) not lower than ...(i)... and with a runway visual range (RVR) not less than ...(ii)...",
    "feedback": "(i) 200 ft (ii) 550 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "To extinguish a fire in the cockpit, you use:\n\n1. a water fire-extinguisher\n2. a powder or chemical fire-extinguisher\n3. a halon fire-extinguisher\n4. a CO2 fire-extinguisher\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The MOCA is 6900 ft. What is the maximum obstacle or terrain height?",
    "feedback": "5830 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "For turbo-propeller aircraft, in the flight preparation stage, the landing distance on at alternate aerodrome shall be less than the available landing distance multiplied by a factor of :",
    "feedback": "0.7"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, the minimum number of crash axes or crowbars on board an aeroplane, whose maximum approved passenger seating configuration is more than 200, is:",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, an operator must select two destination alternates when the appropriate weather reports or forecasts for the destination, or any combination thereof, indicate that during a period commencing ...(i)... hour(s) before and ending ...(ii)... hour(s) after the estimated ...(iii)..., the weather conditions will be below the applicable planning minima.",
    "feedback": "(i) one (ii) one (iii) time of arrival"
  },
  {
    "question": "A piece of equipment on your public transport aircraft fails while you are still parked. The reference document you use to decide on the procedure to follow is:",
    "feedback": "the minimum equipment list."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to Annex 6, what is the definition of an Air Operator Certificate?",
    "feedback": "A certificate authorising an operator to carry out specified commercial air transport operations"
  },
  {
    "question": "Noise abatement procedures for aeroplanes can be found in AIP section:",
    "feedback": "AD 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to OPS regulations, when a commercial transport passenger aircraft has a maximum approved passenger seating configuration of more than 19 passengers, the flight deck compartment door must include:",
    "feedback": "a locking system to prevent any unauthorised access"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true?",
    "feedback": "OCH is referenced to threshold elevation, or, in certain cases, to the aerodrome elevation"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight to Europe, scheduled in MNPS airspace, you expect to cross the 30°W meridian at 2330 UTC ; you will normally be :",
    "feedback": "out of the validity period of organized flight track system"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following describes best the most significant hazard associated with ice breaking off from the airframe of a turbojet aeroplane during take-off?",
    "feedback": "Ingestion into an engine with subsequent damage to the fan and/or compressor blades"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an aeroplane with a tyre pressure of 8 bars, there is a risk of dynamic hydroplaning as soon as the:",
    "feedback": "speed is greater than 98 kt"
  },
  {
    "question": "When using ICAO Noise Abatement Procedure 1 (NADP 1) the flap retraction is commenced at:",
    "feedback": "3000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "A flight with 42 passengers is required to carry sufficient first aid oxygen for ... calculated for the entire flight time which, following de-pressurisation, the aircraft cabin altitude would be greater than ...",
    "feedback": "one passenger; 8000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The complete information regarding the types of goods which the passengers are forbidden from transporting aboard an aircraft is listed in the:",
    "feedback": "ICAO document \"Technical Instructions for the Safe Transport of Dangerous Goods by Air"
  },
  {
    "question": "A category III C precision approach (CAT III C) is an approach with :",
    "feedback": "no runway visual range limits"
  },
  {
    "question": "The greatest possibility of ice buildup, while flying under icing conditions, occurs on :",
    "feedback": "The aircraft front areas."
  },
  {
    "question": "OPS regulations specify the requirements for an Operator to conduct Initial Crew Resource Management (CRM) training.\nWho is authorized to conduct this training?",
    "feedback": "A suitably qualified CRM trainer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Penetration into the North Atlantic ocean airspace is :",
    "feedback": "subject to a mandatory clearance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Whenever practicable, what transponder code should be used to provide recognition of an aircraft which is being subjected to unlawful interference?",
    "feedback": "A 7500"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is not equipped with a wind shear detection system. When commencing a final approach, airspeed increases and the pilot suspects that this is because of a microburst. What is the correct action?",
    "feedback": "Go-around"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, the lowest minima to be used by an operator for circling with a category D aeroplane is a meteorological visibility of:",
    "feedback": "3600 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following forms or information are not required to be carried on all flight?\n\n1) The Operational Flight Plan (OFP)\n2) Mass and balance documentation\n3) NOTAMS\n4) The technical log\n5) Maps and charts\n6) Passenger and cargo manifests",
    "feedback": "6"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following items, required to be on board an aircraft for operating reasons in accordance with the relevant OPS regulations, are classified as dangerous goods?  1) Fire extinguishers 2) Self-inflating life jackets 3) Portable oxygen supplies 4) First-aid kits  The combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "In case of a ditching, the cabin attendants will :\n\n1. evacuate women and children first.\n2. have the passengers embark directly in the liferafts.\n3. prevent passenger movements which may impede the airplane's flotation ability.\n4. ensure the complete evacuation of the airplane.\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the pre-flight preparation, a pilot who is operating a commercial air transport flight with passengers, notices a fault with the only GPS receiver on board. The pilot has access to both the MEL and MMEL, and finds the notes as shown below. How should the effect of the fault be addressed?\nMMEL: May be inoperative provided it is not required for navigationMEL: May be inoperative for VFR by day only, or positioning flights if not required for navigation",
    "feedback": "This flight may be conducted as planned, if it is daylight and the flight is planned according to VFR only"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the event of communication failure in NAT airspace, according to the North Atlantic Operations and Airspace Manual, the pilot must:",
    "feedback": "continue his flight compliance with the last oceanic clearance received and acknowledged by him."
  },
  {
    "question": "According DOC 4444 (ICAO), a wake turbulence non-radar separation minima of 2 minutes shall be applied to :",
    "feedback": "MEDIUM aircraft landing behind a HEAVY aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the required correct configuration for ditching an aircraft?",
    "feedback": "Nose attitude up, gear up, flaps down"
  },
  {
    "question": "An Operator has a fleet of jet aeroplanes of one type. Some aeroplanes have steel brakes and others carbon brakes. How might the taxi procedures for the two variants vary?\nThe aeroplanes with steel brakes should be taxied at a:",
    "feedback": "Lower speed using frequent, short brake applications, whereas the aeroplanes with carbon brakes should be left to accelerate to a higher taxi speed before slowing right down to limit the number of brake applications"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the ICAO Annexes is related to security?",
    "feedback": "Annex 17"
  },
  {
    "question": "When refueling is being performed while passengers are boarding or disembarking the aircraft, it is necessary that: (Annex 6, Part I)",
    "feedback": "Communications be maintained between ground personnel and qualified personnel on board."
  },
  {
    "question": "An operator shall ensure that information relevant to the flight is preserved on the ground for the duration of each flight or series of flights. This includes:\n\n1) appropriate meteorological information\n2) a copy of the operational flight plan and, if required,  the mass and balance documentation\n3) copies of the relevant parts of the aircraft technical log\n4) route specific NOTAM documentation if specifially edited by the operator\n5) special loads notification\n6) copies of the day's performances and limitations with completed charts\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "2,3,4,5"
  },
  {
    "question": "The determination of the aerodrome minimum operating conditions must take the following into account :\n\n1. equipment available for navigation\n2. dimensions and characteristics of the runways\n3. composition of the flight crew\n4. obstacles in the vicinity of approach and missed approach areas\n5. facilities for determining and communicating the weather conditions\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is :",
    "feedback": "1,2,3,4,5"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft having undertaken an anti-icing procedure and having exceeded the protection time of the anti-icing fluid:",
    "feedback": "must undertake a de-icing procedure before a new application of anti-icing fluid before take-off"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which one of the following sets of conditions is most likely to attract birds to an aerodrome ?",
    "feedback": "a refuse tip in close proximity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Choose the option which correctly represents how braking action would be reported in a SNOWTAM:",
    "feedback": "H) 3/4/3"
  },
  {
    "question": "In VMC, a runway should not be chosen as preferential for noise abatement procedures when:",
    "feedback": "it has no ILS or visual approach slope guidance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which statement is correct concerning noise abatement?",
    "feedback": "There is no prohibition on the use of thrust reverse"
  },
  {
    "question": "A rapid decompression may be caused by:  1) a leak in a doorseal during normal pressurized flight 2) loss of a cabin compartment window 3) malfunction of all pressurization systems 4) loss of a cargo-hold door  The combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "2, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the European Regulation on Air Operations. Which of the following statements correctly describes the radio communication equipment required for operations under IFR?",
    "feedback": "The radio communication equipment must be in accordance with the applicable airspace requirements and include at least two independent radio communication systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "Malfunctioning of the automatic pressurisation system is indicated by:\n\n1) a change in environmental sound.\n2) the cabin altitude gauge indicates an abnormal rate of climb\n3) the differential pressure between the exterior and the interior of the aircraft decreases\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1,2,3."
  },
  {
    "question": "In MNPS airspace, the speed reference for turbojet aircraft is the:",
    "feedback": "Mach number."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane has been chartered to transport a group of passengers. Catering is being loaded onto the aeroplane and it includes perishable food items that are being kept cold by packets of dry ice. During passenger briefing, one of the passengers, who is a chef, has food and dry ice in the cabin baggage. \nIs there any difference in the way the dry ice is considered?",
    "feedback": "Yes, the dry ice used for catering is part of the aeroplane equipment while the dry ice brought by the chef is controlled by the Technical Instructions for Dangerous Goods"
  },
  {
    "question": "The coverage angle of the regulatory white navigation/position lights, continuously lit in flight and located at the rear of the aircraft, is :",
    "feedback": "140°"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft operator within the EU intends to apply for an AOC. Referring to the part of the EASA AOC template, which option most accurately identifies the \"Issuing Authority\"?",
    "feedback": "It is the relevant Member State Competent Authority or EASA"
  },
  {
    "question": "The minimum navigation equipment required for an aircraft flying without restriction in MNPS airspace can be at the very least :",
    "feedback": "Two inertial navigation units."
  },
  {
    "question": "Windshear may be described as a change in wind direction and/or speed in space, including updrafts and downdrafts. To counter the effects of windshear the amount of control action that is required is :",
    "feedback": "substantial"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the EPR probe becomes covered with ice,  EPR indications will be:",
    "feedback": "Greater than the actual."
  },
  {
    "question": "The minimum lateral separation in the NAT region is:",
    "feedback": "60 NM between aircraft meeting minimum navigation performance specifications"
  },
  {
    "question": "A category II operation (CAT II) is an instrument precision approach and landing using ILS or MLS with: :",
    "feedback": "a DH below 200 ft but not lower than 100 ft and a RVR of not less than 300 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "When flying in straight and level flight at FL 290 for some considerable time a small leak develops in the cabin which causes a slow depressurisation, this can be seen on the cabin rate of climb indicator which will indicate :",
    "feedback": "a rate of climb"
  },
  {
    "question": "Following an emergency landing which will need an escape from the aircraft, you will:\n\n1 - remain on the runway,\n2 - clear the runway using the first available taxiway,\n3 - keep one engine or the APU running in order to maintain the electrical power supply on,\n4 - turn off all systems.\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1,4."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is scheduled to perform a short flight where the maximum planned altitude is FL260. During flight preparations it becomes apparent that the aeroplane is not RVSM compliant due to a technical malfunction that has been deferred to the MEL.\nWhat, if any, altitude restrictions apply for the flight?",
    "feedback": "None, as the flight is planned to operate below RVSM airspace"
  },
  {
    "question": "The tip vortices circulate about each wing tip :",
    "feedback": "from the underwing toward the upper side of the wing."
  },
  {
    "question": "In compliance with EASA AIR OPS, in order to carry hazardous materials on board a public transport aircraft, they must be accompanied by:",
    "feedback": "a dangerous goods transport document"
  },
  {
    "question": "The wake turbulence:",
    "feedback": "starts during the rotation and stops as soon as the airplane's wheels touch the ground."
  },
  {
    "question": "For the flight crew members, quickly-fitted oxygen masks are compulsory on board any pressurized aircraft flying at a pressure altitude greater than :",
    "feedback": "25 000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "The actions required by the cockpit crew on experiencing smoke in the cockpit are:",
    "feedback": "Put on oxygen masks and goggles, select 100% oxygen, identify cause of smoke, isolate electrical equipment as appropriate, continue with emergency checklist"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where in the Operations Manual can you find information about abnormal and emergency procedures if you are acting as a captain under AOC?",
    "feedback": "Part B"
  },
  {
    "question": "If smoke appears in the air conditioning, the initial action to be taken by the flight deck crew is to :",
    "feedback": "Put on the mask and goggles."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the recommended noise abatement procedures contained in the ICAO, DOC 8168 Volume I part V, data available indicates that the procedure which results in noise relief during the part of the procedure close to the airport :",
    "feedback": "is procedure A (NADP 1)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The highest risk of bird strikes occurs:",
    "feedback": "under 2500 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the case of overheating of the brakes following the landing, the appropriate action at the parking position is:\n\n1) set parking brake on\n2) set parking brake off, with chocks in position\n3) spray water on the brakes\n4) ventilate the brakes\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "2, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with the OPS regulations, a single deck aeroplane, equipped with an approved seating capacity of 71 seats and carrying passengers, must be equipped with at least:",
    "feedback": "1 megaphone"
  },
  {
    "question": "To fight a fire in an air-conditioned cargo hold:",
    "feedback": "you turn off the cargo hold ventilation and extinguish fire."
  },
  {
    "question": "Who shall amend the MEL after any applicable change to the MMEL within the acceptable timescales?",
    "feedback": "The operator"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying from Frankfurt, Germany, to Quebec, Canada. While in the NAT HLA, an in-flight emergency calls for a diversion to Keflavik, Iceland. The aircraft lands at maximum landing mass and vacates the runway. Brake temperature warnings light up. The crew becomes concerned about the possibility of a brake fire. An appropriate action would be to ......",
    "feedback": "stop on the taxiway, do not apply the parking brake and request the Airport Fire Service to attend"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, a commander shall ensure that the amount of usable fuel remaining in flight is not less than the fuel required to proceed to an aerodrome where a safe landing can be made with:",
    "feedback": "final reserve fuel remaining"
  },
  {
    "question": "Observations of the prevailing meteorological conditions can help pilots decide whether to take off or to delay until conditions improve.\nThe following meteorological conditions would indicate the presence of low-level wind shear and would require a pilot to delay take-off:\n1) Precipitation falling from the base of a cloud but evaporating before reaching the ground2) Wind socks responding to different winds3) Visibile moisture and a visibility of less than 10 km4) Strong, gusty surface winds, especially where the aerodrome is located near hills5) Smoke plumes sheared, with upper and lower sections moving in different directions",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 4, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight to Europe, scheduled in MNPS airspace, you expect to cross the 30°W meridian at 0300 UTC. You will normally be :",
    "feedback": "in a night-time organised track system"
  },
  {
    "question": "Unless sufficient life rafts to carry all persons on board are carried, on overwater flights, an operator shall not operate an aeroplane at a distance away from land, which is suitable for making an emergency landing, greater than that corresponding to ...(i)... minutes at cruising speed or ...(ii)... nautical miles, whichever is the lesser, for aeroplanes capable of continuing the flight to an aerodrome with the critical power unit(s) becoming inoperative at any point along the route or planned diversions.",
    "feedback": "(i) 120 minutes   (ii) 400 nautical miles"
  },
  {
    "question": "A bird strike most likely occurs close-by:",
    "feedback": "a garbage place"
  },
  {
    "question": "According with DOC 4444 (ICAO), a wake turbulence non-radar separation minima of 3 minutes shall be applied to :",
    "feedback": "LIGHT aircraft landing behind a MEDIUM aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "After anti-icing has been completed, a pre-departure inspection revels presence of frost, ice or snow. The correct action is to:",
    "feedback": "carry out a new de-icing/anti-icing procedure"
  },
  {
    "question": "If notified that a package of dangerous goods is damaged, who is responsible for arranging for its removal?",
    "feedback": "It must be removed under the Operator's responsibility"
  },
  {
    "question": "The ICAO Annex dealing with the safe transport of dangerous goods by air is:",
    "feedback": "Annex 18"
  },
  {
    "question": "When taking-off behind a wide-body aircraft, with wind coming from the left side, you adopt a path, whenever possible :",
    "feedback": "distinct from the preceding airplane, by remaining at the left of and above its path."
  },
  {
    "question": "The ICAO procedure designed to collect and disseminate information on bird strikes to aircraft is called:",
    "feedback": "IBIS (ICAO Bird Strike Information System)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where would you find information on bird migration areas/routes?",
    "feedback": "AIP ENR 5.6"
  },
  {
    "question": "In case of total loss of communications, if an aircraft operating in MNPS airspace is unable to continue its flight in accordance with its ATC clearance, it must offset from the assigned route by 15 NM and climb by 1000 ft or descend by 500 ft to a level which differs from those normally used if flying:",
    "feedback": "at FL 410"
  },
  {
    "question": "When en-route from Cairo to Larnaca, the flight crew is suddenly subjected to unlawful interference by two hijackers. The Commander sets the transponder Mode A Code 7500 without being noticed. ATC then asks the flight crew over the radio to confirm the code 7500. However, the flight crew does not respond. How should the crew's decision not to respond be interpreted by ATC?",
    "feedback": "The use of Code 7500 is intentional and correctly selected by the crew"
  },
  {
    "question": "The operator shall only select an aerodrome as an ETOPS en-route alternate aerodrome when the appropriate weather reports or forecasts, or any combination thereof, indicate that, between the anticipated time of landing until one hour after the latest possible time of landing, conditions will exist at or above the planning minima for a circling approach calculated by adding the additional limits of:",
    "feedback": "MDA/H + 400 ft, RVR/VIS + 1500 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the absence of wind and without the astronomic precession effect, an aircraft would, at a constant gyro heading, follow a :",
    "feedback": "great circle line"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the cockpit preparation for the first flight of the day, you are verifying the MEL items effective for the aircraft you are about to fly and it states that one of the two autopilots is inoperative. The MEL item states that RNP AR approaches requiring less than 0.3 NM of accuracy are prohibited with 1 autopilot inoperative, and a further degradation with a failure of the second autopilot would prohibit flights in RVSM. \nWhich statement is correct?",
    "feedback": "RNP AR approach is not allowed under the the current dispatch conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "A hand water fire extinguisher should be used on a fire of:",
    "feedback": "paper, fabric, carpet"
  },
  {
    "question": "If a pilot has coupled the automatic pilot to the directional gyro equipped with a rate correction device set for astronomical precession, the course followed by the aircraft (in still air conditions) is:",
    "feedback": "a great circle"
  },
  {
    "question": "An act of unlawful interference is suspected. What are the appropriate measures?",
    "feedback": "The aircraft should be searched for explosives"
  },
  {
    "question": "A hand fire extinguisher needs to be used in the cabin. What should the crew member do, prior to using the fire extinguisher, in order to most effectively reduce the risk of inhaling toxic fumes or smoke?",
    "feedback": "Put on portable Protective Breathing Equipment"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the \"No Smoking\" and \"Fasten your Seat Belts\" sign requirements?",
    "feedback": "Aeroplanes in which not all passenger seats are visible from the flight crew seat(s) shall be equipped with a means of indicating to all passengers and cabin crew when seat belts shall be fastened and when smoking is not allowed"
  },
  {
    "question": "On a polar stereographic chart where the earth convergence between 2 points located on the parallel 60°N is 20°, the great circle maximum cross-track difference with the straight line joining the 2 points is :",
    "feedback": "9.2 NM."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to the European Regulations on Air Operations, an Operator shall not operate a turbine propeller powered, or an aeroplane with a maximum certificated Take-off Mass in excess of 5700 kg, or having a maximum Operational Passenger Seating Configuration (MOPSC) of more than nine seats, or a turbojet powered aeroplane, unless it is equipped with an altitude alerting system capable of alerting the flight crew when ......",
    "feedback": "approaching a pre-selected altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who initially is responsible for ensuring that cargo for air transportation as dangerous goods is not prohibited?",
    "feedback": "The shipper when completing the shipper's declaration for dangerous goods"
  },
  {
    "question": "The MNPS airspace extends vertically between flight levels:",
    "feedback": "285 and 420"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the European Regulation on Air Operations as applicable to Commercial Air Transport operations. An aircraft is on a transatlantic flight. Due to unforeseen circumstances, the commander has to extend the Flight Duty Period (FDP) by three hours in order to allow the aircraft to continue to its destination. What has to be taken into consideration?",
    "feedback": "This extension is allowed, provided an augmented crew is available"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to OPS regulations, a life jacket is mandatory for each person on board a land aeroplane, when flying over water at a distance from the shore of more than:",
    "feedback": "50 NM"
  },
  {
    "question": "Following detection of a slow decompression and the automatic deployment of the oxygen masks from the passenger service units in the cabin, the first actions to be performed by the cabin crew are to ......",
    "feedback": "don the nearest oxygen mask and alert the Commander"
  },
  {
    "question": "What kind of dangerous goods is specified by the label?",
    "feedback": "Corrosive substances"
  },
  {
    "question": "Most modern aeroplanes have fire extinguishers in the toilet compartments which are:",
    "feedback": "automatic and self activated by heat"
  },
  {
    "question": "A braking action of 0.25 and below reported on a SNOWTAM is :",
    "feedback": "poor"
  },
  {
    "question": "A polar track is a track part of which is included in an area where the horizontal component of the earth magnetic field is less than :",
    "feedback": "6 micro-tesla"
  },
  {
    "question": "What should cabin crew members do if they smell smoke in the cabin, but there is no visible sign of the source?",
    "feedback": "Notify the pilots immediately"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:  g, the longitude difference Lm, the average latitude Lo, the latitude of the tangent  The correct formula of the conversion angle applied, during a transoceanic and polar navigation, is equal to :",
    "feedback": "g/2.sin Lm"
  },
  {
    "question": "The abbreviation \"OTS\" stands for:",
    "feedback": "Organised Track System"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to OPS regulation, a quality system:",
    "feedback": "shall be established by all operators"
  },
  {
    "question": "Item D of a SNOWTAM gives the cleared length of a runway in metres. If this is less than the published length, how is this reported?",
    "feedback": "By a four figure group added to item D, which gives the length in metres"
  },
  {
    "question": "At which levels may Reduced Vertical Separation Minimum (RVSM)  be used within NAT region?",
    "feedback": "Between FL290 and FL410."
  },
  {
    "question": "Under what conditions can the choice of runway disregard any noise abatement approach procedures?\n1) Crosswind > 10 knots2) Tailwind, gusts of more than 5 knots above the mean wind3) Visibility < 3000 m",
    "feedback": "2"
  },
  {
    "question": "When taking-off, in winter conditions, the wing contamination by ice or  frost will cause the following effects:\n\n1 - an increase in the take-off distance\n2 - a diminution of the take-off run\n3 - an increase in the stalling speed\n4 - a diminution of the stalling speed\n5 - a diminution of the climb gradient\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is :",
    "feedback": "1, 3, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "While flying en-route, the crew observes white smoke coming out from the radar panel, situated in the middle console, with the smell of burning insulation. The recommended actions for the crew to take are:",
    "feedback": "Switch off the radar, maintain safe flight conditions, and follow the checklist"
  },
  {
    "question": "The pilot uses a South polar stereographic chart with grid parallel with the zero meridian and Grid North in the direction of geographic North along this meridian.\nThe aircraft position is 80°S 130°E, its true route is 110°, the grid route at this moment is :",
    "feedback": "240°."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to OPS regulations, a pilot is not assigned to operate an aeroplane as part of the minimum certificated crew, either as pilot flying or pilot non-flying unless he/she has carried out:",
    "feedback": "as pilot-in-command or as co-pilot at least three take-off and three landings in an aeroplane or an approved flight simulator of the type used, in the preceding 90 days."
  },
  {
    "question": "On arriving overhead an isolated aerodrome, the commander of a turbojet engined aircraft should have a minimum quantity of fuel (additional reserve, including the final reserve) sufficient for flying during:",
    "feedback": "2 hours with normal cruise consumption."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is flying in heavy rain. To carry out a safe approach, it is necessary to :",
    "feedback": "increase its approach speed, because the rain affects the lift by deteriorating the boundary layer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which EASA regulations prescribe requirements for approved maintenance organisations?",
    "feedback": "EASA Part 145"
  },
  {
    "question": "A twin-engine aircraft experiences an engine failure, followed by fire in engine # 2. The aircraft lands and stops on the runway and the fire fighting services start extinguishing the fire. Cabin crew members see smoke coming from engine # 2. Communication with the flight crew is not possible. What should the cabin crew do?",
    "feedback": "Evacuate by the left side of the aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "For aeroplanes having a seating capacity of more than 44 passengers, it must be shown by actual demonstration that the maximum seating capacity, including the required number of crew members, can be evacuated from the aeroplane to the ground in :",
    "feedback": "90 seconds"
  },
  {
    "question": "During take-off preparation, windshear can be predicted by observing:\n1) Lenticular clouds close to the airfield which is located in a montaineous area2) Precipitation that is not reaching the surface3) The wind sock4) Smoke from chimneys which is divided in different directions instead of moving steadily in one direction5) Steady rain6) Fog",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with (ICAO) DOC 8168 - OPS, noise preferential routes are established to ensure that departing and arriving aeroplanes avoid overflying noise-sensitive areas in the vicinity of the aerodrome as far as practicable. In establishing noise preferential routes :",
    "feedback": "no turns should be required coincident with a reduction of power associated with a noise abatement procedure."
  },
  {
    "question": "A passenger wishes to transport several lithium power banks, which are used to run or charge other devices. Considering the requirements for transport of lithium batteries by air, which of the following is correct?\nThese power banks:",
    "feedback": "Are considered as batteries and only a small number of spare batteries can be carried in hand luggage. Otherwise, they must be separately shipped in a cargo aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "What kind of dangerous goods is specified by the label?",
    "feedback": "Infectious substances"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is responsible for establishing training progreammes that are intended to minimise opportunities for unlawful interference with flights?",
    "feedback": "The Operator"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of these options is one of the purposes of the cabin crew security training?",
    "feedback": "Train cabin crew on different procedures about how to deal with a hijacker"
  },
  {
    "question": "A fire extinguisher must be carried in the cockpit. It should contain:",
    "feedback": "BCF"
  },
  {
    "question": "To avoid wake turbulence, when departing behind a larger aircraft, the pilot should manoeuver :",
    "feedback": "Above and upwind from the larger aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS (Aerodrome Operating Minima), the lowest minima to be used by an operator in a category B aeroplane for circling are :",
    "feedback": "MDH=500 ft and visibility=1600 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a transoceanic and polar flight, the transport precession is the rotation in degrees of the gyro North with respect to the:",
    "feedback": "true North"
  },
  {
    "question": "As a commander, if you are notified that a package of dangerous goods appears to be damaged, you:",
    "feedback": "ensure that arrangements are made for its removal."
  },
  {
    "question": "Following an accident, the operator of an aircraft equipped with a flight recorder must keep the original recordings for a minimum period of:",
    "feedback": "60 days."
  },
  {
    "question": "Your flight manual does not include specific supplementary  information on landing distances on wet runways and the service bulletins or weather reports indicate that the runway may be wet at the estimated time of arrival. The required landing distance on a dry runway must be increased by:",
    "feedback": "15 %"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, the take-off climb procedures for noise abatement to be specified by the operator should be:",
    "feedback": "for any one aeroplane type, the same for all aerodromes"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is cruising at FL370 when the pilot suddenly starts feeling a slight discomfort in the ears and a \"popping\" sensation. What could be the cause?",
    "feedback": "If the cabin altitude is also rising, there could be a pressurisation system failure"
  },
  {
    "question": "Following a fire in the passenger cabin, the cabin crew should first...",
    "feedback": "move passengers away from the source of the fire"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is scheduled to depart from an airfield which is closing soon. The current METAR is reporting freezing fog. The airport's de-ice and anti-ice equipment is out of service due to a flat tyre. The company has expressed that the flight must remain on schedule.\nWhat shall the pilots do?",
    "feedback": "Delay the take-off until the equipment is available"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do the flight and ground crew have to take into account when performing anti-icing/de-icing procedures on the ground?\n1) Time of the anti-icing/de-icing application2) Airport location and elevation3) Aircraft type specific procedures4) Competence of the de-icing staff",
    "feedback": "1, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "At 18h40min UTC, a complete failure of the inertial systems of an aircraft flying on the LONDON- ANCHORAGE line occurs in the geographic North pole region. The wind is nil, the grid heading at this moment is 315°. The crew then uses the Sun to continue the flight. The bearing of the Sun on occurence of the failure is :  NOTE: The time equation is nil. The chart used is a polar stereographic chart whose grid is parallel with the zero meridian, the Grid North is in direction of the geographic North pole.",
    "feedback": "325°."
  },
  {
    "question": "Wind shear is:",
    "feedback": "a vertical or horizontal wind velocity and / or wind direction variation over a short distance"
  },
  {
    "question": "Wake turbulence should be taken into account when :",
    "feedback": "a much heavier aeroplane has landed just previously on the same runway, a light crosswind condition exist and all high-lift devices are being used."
  },
  {
    "question": "How far from an enroute alternate airfield can a 2-engined turbojet aeroplane with more than 20 seats and a MTOM of 38.000 kg be flown?",
    "feedback": "60 minutes at the one engine out speed."
  },
  {
    "question": "If inflammable gaseous materials, like propane for example, are set on fire, the following extinguisher types should be used for fire fighting:",
    "feedback": "BCF and CO2 type"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the event of a contingency which required an en-route diversion to an alternate aerodrome across the direction of the prevailing \"NAT\" traffic flow and if prior ATC clearance cannot be obtained an aircraft not able to maintain its assigned flight level should:",
    "feedback": "Start its descent while turning to acquire a track separated by 15 NM from its assigned route or track."
  },
  {
    "question": "After landing and heavy manual braking, you have a very short turn around time. Which considerations have to be taken?",
    "feedback": "If the allotted time for cooling the brakes is not considered, this could cause the fusible plugs of the tyre to melt and pop out during taxi for departure"
  },
  {
    "question": "The flight deck door should be capable of being :",
    "feedback": "locked from within the compartment"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, for aeroplanes with a maximum certificated take-off mass over 5700 kg, flight data recorders shall be capable of retaining the data recorded during at least the last:",
    "feedback": "25 hours of operation."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to OPS, the characteristics of de-icing and anti-icing fluids to be used for your aircraft can be found in:",
    "feedback": "the operations manual"
  },
  {
    "question": "90 % of bird strikes occur :",
    "feedback": "under 500 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "A category III B precision approach (CAT III B) is an approach which may be carried out with a runway visual range of at least :",
    "feedback": "75 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "The minimum equipment list (MEL) states the equipment which can be  inoperative when undertaking a flight and the additional procedures to be observed accordingly. \n\nThis list is established by:",
    "feedback": "the operator, and it is inserted in the operations manual"
  },
  {
    "question": "In a microburst combined with a violent storm the winds at :",
    "feedback": "low altitude diverge from the center of the phenomenon and the atmospheric pressure increases by a few hectopascals."
  },
  {
    "question": "When the weather conditions require an alternate aerodrome to be available on take-off, the latter shall be located, for aircraft with three or more engines, at an equivalent distance not exceeding :",
    "feedback": "2 hours of flight at cruising speed with 1 engine inoperative"
  },
  {
    "question": "The time of useful consciousness in case of an explosive decompression at an altitude of \n40 000 ft is:",
    "feedback": "12 seconds."
  },
  {
    "question": "For twin-engined aircraft, the takeoff alternate shall be located at a distance that : (Annex 6, Part I)",
    "feedback": "Does not exceed the equivalent of one hour of flight time, at cruising speed with only one engine operative."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to OPS regulations, an operator shall not operate a turbine propeller powered aeroplane with a maximum certificated take-off mass in excess of 5700 kg or having a maximum approved passenger seating configuration of more than nine seats or a turbojet powered aeroplane unless it is equipped with an altitude alterting system capable of alerting the flight crew when:",
    "feedback": "Deviating from a preselected altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, an aeroplane whose maximum approved passenger seating configuration is 10 seats must be equipped with:",
    "feedback": "1 hand fire extinguisher in the cockpit and 1 hand fire extinguisher in the passenger compartment."
  },
  {
    "question": "You are working for an airline that has been contracted to deliver humanitarian aid. You have been flying all day with the same aircraft and are heading back from headquarters to your last flight of the day. No passengers are on board, only cargo. Do you need to perform a security check on the cargo?",
    "feedback": "Yes, it still needs to be checked to find any dangerous goods that could endanger safety"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, an operator must select a take-off alternate:",
    "feedback": "if it would not be possible to return to the aerodrome of departure for meteorological or performance reasons"
  },
  {
    "question": "H2O extinguishers are fit to fight fires on:",
    "feedback": "carbonaceous materials"
  },
  {
    "question": "In icing conditions and after the application of an anti-icing fluid on your airplane, you are waiting to take-off by:\n\n1. avoiding positioning yourself in the engine jet wash of the preceding aircraft\n2. avoiding positioning yourself in the turbo-props wash of the preceding aircraft \n3. positioning yourself in the engine jet wash of the preceding aircraft \n4. positioning yourself in the turbo-props wash of the preceding aircraft \n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which ICAO document do you follow for noise abatement procedures?",
    "feedback": "ICAO DOC 8168"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the difference between OTS routes in NAT MNPS airspace and routes T9, T13, and T16?",
    "feedback": "Routes T9, T13 and T16 are routes between Northern Europe and Spain/Canaries/Lisbon FIR"
  },
  {
    "question": "An operator shall not operate an aeroplane first issued with an individual Certificate of Airworthiness on or after 1 April 1998, which has a maximum certificated take-off mass over 5700 kg, unless it is equipped with a cockpit voice recorder which records:\n\n1) voice communications transmitted from or received on the flight deck by radio\n2) the aural envionment of the flight deck\n3) the cabin attendants communications in the cabin using the aeroplane's interphone system\n4) voice communications of flight crew members on the flight deck using the aeroplane's interphone system\n5) voice or audio signals identifying navigation or approach aids introduced into a headset or speaker\n6) voice communications of flight crew members on the flight deck using the public address system, if installed\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 4, 5, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is responsible for providing on Operation Manual in accordance with EASA AIR OPS Subpart P for the use and guidance of the operations personnel?",
    "feedback": "the aircraft operator"
  },
  {
    "question": "CO2 type extinguishers are suitable to fight fire on:\n\n1) carbonaceous materials\n2) flammable liquids\n3) electrical equipment\n4) metals\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "For stable clouds:\n\n1- the most favourable temperatures for icing are between 0°C and -10°C\n2- the most favourable temperatures for icing are between 0°C and -15°C\n3- icing becomes rare at t < -18°C\n4- icing becomes rare at t < -30°C\n5- the diameter of water droplets is between 0.002 and 0.03mm\n6- the diameter of water droplets is between 0.004 and 0.2mm\n\nWhich of the following combinations contains all the correct statements?",
    "feedback": "1 - 3 - 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "The attitudes to be adopted by the passengers, sitting in the travelling direction, in case of an emergency landing are: \n \n1. legs together and feet flat on the floor,\n2. head resting against the back of the front seat,\n3. forearms on the armrests,\n4. seat belt very tightly fastened,\n5. head resting on the forearms.\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 4, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "To use passengers oxygen in case of severe cabin smoke is:",
    "feedback": "useless because the toxical cabin smoke is mixed with the breathing oxygen."
  },
  {
    "question": "The protection time of an anti-icing fluid depends on:\n\n1. the type and intensity of the showers\n2. the ambient temperature\n3. the relative humidity\n4. the direction and speed of the wind\n5. the temperature of the airplane skin\n6. the type of fluid, its concentration and temperature\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, where no outer marker or equivalent position exists, if the reported RVR/Visibility is less than the applicable minima, the approach shall not be continued beyond:",
    "feedback": "1000 ft above the aerodrome/heliport"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, the commander of a turbojet engine aeroplane should have a final reserve fuel for:",
    "feedback": "30 minutes of flight at holding speed at 1500 ft above aerodrome elevation in standard conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "A crew is flying from London Heathrow, UK to New York JFK, USA and is within the NAT High Level Airspace (HLA) at FL360. A hydraulic warning light has come on, which may necessitate a change of level. The in-flight contingency procedure requires an offset from the assigned route.\nWhat would be the initial action if prior clearance cannot be obtained?",
    "feedback": "A turn to the right of track of at least 30° towards the nearest alternate, which is, according to the flight plan, Keflavik, Iceland"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with DOC 4444 (ICAO) when a MEDIUM and a LIGHT aircraft are using the same runway, or parallel runways separated by less than 760 m, (in approach or departure phases of flight), shall be applied a wake turbulence radar separation minima of :",
    "feedback": "5 NM"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, for a pressurised aeroplane, certificated to fly at altitudes more than 25000 ft, all occupants of flight deck seats on flight deck duty shall be suppied with supplemental oxygen during a period in no case less than:",
    "feedback": "2 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "The height below which an aeroplane should not jettison fuel is:",
    "feedback": "1800 m / 6000 ft above ground"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft experiences a bird strike that results in significant damage. What shall be done by the commander after landing?",
    "feedback": "Write a bird strike report"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a ditching situation, what is the highest priority of the aircraft Commander during the manoeuvre?",
    "feedback": "The control of the aircraft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which is an operational requirement concerning ice, snow, or frost on aircraft surfaces?",
    "feedback": "Takeff shall not be commenced unless the external surfaces are clear of any deposit which might adversely affect the performance and/or controllability of the aeroplane"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight it is necessary to use hand held fire extinguishers for fighting a small localized fire in the passenger cabin. The crew members know that the most effective method for discharging the extinguishing agent is by holding the extinguisher:",
    "feedback": "approximately 1.5 - 2.5 m from the source of the fire"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the H field of a SNOWTAM the information displayed is 0,25. This means that the braking action is:",
    "feedback": "poor."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to ICAO Annex 6, what shall the operator establish for the use and guidance of operational personnel, as part of its safety management system?",
    "feedback": "A flight safety documents system"
  },
  {
    "question": "In establishing a noise abatement procedure, an operator should:",
    "feedback": "ensure that safety has priority over noise requirements and that the procedure does not significantly increase the pilots workload"
  },
  {
    "question": "A pilot whose aircraft does not have MNPS certification has to fly via the SHANNON-GANDER great circle. The flight must be planned to take place :",
    "feedback": "at flight level FL 280 or less."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EU Air Operations Regulations, what are the minimum safety-related roles required as part of the management system for an operator classified as complex?",
    "feedback": "Safety Manager and Safety Review Board"
  },
  {
    "question": "In the \"worst case\" scenario of recovery from the effects of a microburst, having increased to full go-around power, in co-ordinating power and pitch it may be necessary to :",
    "feedback": "increase the pitch angle until the stick shaker is felt and hold at slightly below this angle"
  },
  {
    "question": "The terminal VOR transmittes the following weather data. When do you expect carburettor icing?",
    "feedback": "Outside Air Temperature (OAT) : +10°C\nDew Point (DEWP) : +7°C"
  },
  {
    "question": "A light aircraft is landing at a busy airport which operates multiple runways. Which runway should the pilot choose as preferential to avoid wake turbulence after a HEAVY aircraft landing?",
    "feedback": "RWY18, 13 kt crosswind"
  },
  {
    "question": "What would be evident during a rapid decompression?\n1) Violent rush of gas from lungs2) Expansion of body gases3) Blast of air to the exterior4) Mist in the cabin",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "According with DOC 4444 (ICAO), a wake turbulence radar separation minima of 9,3 Km (5,0 NM) shall be applied when a :",
    "feedback": "LIGHT aircraft is crossing behind a MEDIUM aircraft, at the same altitude or less than 300 m (1 000.ft)"
  },
  {
    "question": "When requested by an Authority to produce the aircraft documentation required to be carried on board, the commander:",
    "feedback": "shall comply within a reasonable period of time."
  },
  {
    "question": "The most significant factor that affects the time of useful conciousness (TUC) for each flight crew member is...",
    "feedback": "altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "A class A fire is a fire of:",
    "feedback": "solid material, generally of organic nature"
  },
  {
    "question": "While approaching the outer-marker, the tower informs you about the presence of a microburst. You will expect to encounter:",
    "feedback": "windshears (vertical and horizontal)."
  },
  {
    "question": "For an airplane with a  tyre pressure of 12 bars, there is a risk of dynamic hydroplaning as soon as the  :\n\n1- water height is equal to the depth of the tyre grooves.\n2- speed is greater than 114 kt.\n3- water height is equal to the half of the depth of the tyre grooves.\n4- speed is greater than 83 kt.\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is :",
    "feedback": "1 and 2."
  },
  {
    "question": "In normal flight, what is the position of the emergency lighting switch?",
    "feedback": "ARMED"
  },
  {
    "question": "A class B fire is a fire of:",
    "feedback": "liquid or liquefiable solid"
  },
  {
    "question": "A turbojet aeroplane is experiencing a midair emergency, forcing the aeroplane to make an emergency landing at the nearest suitable aerodrome. Altough the aeroplane is undamaged after landing, the pilot decides than an emergency evacuation of the passengers is required. The emergency evacuation checklist states the following:\nParking brake: SETAll engines: OFFEvacuation: INITIATE\nWhich of the following statements is correct?",
    "feedback": "This checklist ensures that the outside of the aeroplane is safe before people leave the relative safety of the cabin"
  },
  {
    "question": "The chart type is polar stereographic with the grid parallel to the zero meridian, and Grid North in the direction of the North geographic pole. The gyro is not fitted with a rate correction device.\nThe gyro-magnetic compass of an aircraft standing at an aerodrome located at 59°57'N 010°30'E is switched to free gyro mode at 14.00 UTC, with gyro North being aligned with Grid North and the gyro heading reading 120°. A technical problem delays take off until 16.30 UTC. The gyro, whose mechanical precession is zero, was not reset prior to take off.\nThe error (E) at the time of alignment on this runway will be :",
    "feedback": "+32.5°."
  },
  {
    "question": "During the approach, when a wind shear is encountered, you should:\n1) Be stable before reaching 800 ft AGL2) Minimise thrust reduction if headwind increases3) Accept a runway that is less prone to wind shear4) Use, whenever possible, ILS or a path indicator",
    "feedback": "2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "For a given aircraft and runway contamination, increased pressure altitude will:",
    "feedback": "increases the hydroplaning speed."
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following situations could lead to the pilot of a light aircraft carrying out a precautionary landing?",
    "feedback": "Fuel shortage, deteriorating weather, or approaching darkness"
  },
  {
    "question": "Noise abatement shall not be the determining factor in the designation of a runway, under the following circumstances :  1. when cross wind component, including gust, exceeds 15 knots. 2. when the tail wind component, including gust, exceeds 5 knots. 3. when the runway is not clear or dry.  The combination regrouping all the correct statements is :",
    "feedback": "1,2,3."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, what is the planning minima for a destination alternate with a non-precision approach available?",
    "feedback": "Non-precision minima (RVR and the ceiling at or above MDH) plus 200 ft/1000 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "An operator shall not operate an aeroplane unless it is equipped with navigation/position lights for flights:",
    "feedback": "By night"
  },
  {
    "question": "Aircraft flight characteristics including performance, stability, and control may be affected by icing. Compared to the effects of icing in flight, the effects encountered on the ground ......",
    "feedback": "may be totally different, due to the accumulation of frost, snow or ice on unprotected aircraft areas"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS (Aerodrome Operating Minima - General), it is established, among other considerations, that an Operator must take full account of Aeroplane Categories. The criteria taken into consideration for classification of Aeroplanes by Categories is the indicated airspeed at threshold (Vat), which is equal to the stalling speed at the maximum landing mass (Vso) multiplied by 1,3. Corresponding Aeroplane Category when Vat is from 141 kt to 165 kt is :",
    "feedback": "D"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which part of the Operations Manual would you find information regarding ermergency evacuation procedures?",
    "feedback": "Part B"
  },
  {
    "question": "An Operator has approval to carry Dangerous Goods. During the preflight walk around, the Commander observes the loading of a cargo compartment. He/she notices that there are three packages labelled with Label 2 with different Transport Indexes (TIS), and one package labelled with Label 4. The packages are not part of a shipment under a special arrangement.\nIs it permitted to carry these packages?",
    "feedback": "Yes, the packages can be transported without an additional specific Competent Authority approval"
  },
  {
    "question": "When setting up a minimum noise climb, the minimum height at which a power reduction shall be allowed is :",
    "feedback": "240 m (800 ft)"
  },
  {
    "question": "The M.M.E.L. (Master Minimum Equipment List) is drawn up by :",
    "feedback": "the manufacturer."
  },
  {
    "question": "An acceptable timescale for submitting the amended MEL to the competent authority is .... from the effective date specified in the approved change to the MMEL:",
    "feedback": "90 days"
  },
  {
    "question": "What information is to be found in a SNOWTAM?",
    "feedback": "Braking action"
  },
  {
    "question": "If a fire occurs onboard, to protect themselves from fumes and smoke before extinguishing the fire, the flight attendants should:",
    "feedback": "Put on protective breathing equipment"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS regulations, an IFR flight with no alternate airfield can be undertaken only if the minimum weather conditions stipulated in the regulations are effective for at least :",
    "feedback": "1 hour before to at least 1 hour after the expected time of arrival"
  },
  {
    "question": "If the static source to an airspeed indicator (ASI) becomes blocked during a descent the instrument will:",
    "feedback": "over-read"
  },
  {
    "question": "Why should oxygen masks not be used when the cabin is affected by smoke?",
    "feedback": "Because the mask allows the smoke to mix with the oxygen"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the flight of two aircraft in MNPS airspace with a leading aircraft flying at higher speed, the longitudinal spacing must be at least :",
    "feedback": "5 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "In oder to minimise the delay to departure it has been decided to reduce the turnaround time by boarding passengers while the aeroplane is being refuelled with Jet A1. Provided this is approved at the airport, the following statements are correct regarding the procedures that must be in place:\n1) All doors must be open2) Communications must be established between the ground crew supervising the refuelling and the qualified personnel on board3) Crew, passengers and personnel should be warned that refuelling is taking place4) \"No Smoking\" and \"Fasten Seat Belt\" signs must both be on5) The minimum cabin crew complement must be on board",
    "feedback": "2, 3, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the definition for a microburst?\nA microburst lasts for about 1 to 5 minutes and is a highly concentrated and powerful ......",
    "feedback": "Feedback not found"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the definition for a microburst?\nA microburst lasts for about 1 to 5 minutes and is a highly concentrated and powerful ......",
    "feedback": "downdraft of air, typically less than 5 km across"
  },
  {
    "question": "Just after passing V1 during a take-off ground roll, but before rotating, you suddenly hear a fire warning bell and notice the illumination of the left engine fire warning light of your twin-engine airplane. Your first action is to...",
    "feedback": "continue the take-off, stabilize the aircraft and climb"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, in establishing the aerodrome operating minima which will apply to any particular operation, an operator must take full account of:  1) equipment available on the aircraft 2) dimensions and characteristics of the runways 3) composition of the flight crew 4) obstacles in the approach and missed approach areas 5) means to determine and report the meteorological conditions  The combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "ICAO (International Civil Aviation Organization) Appendix 18 is a document dealing with :",
    "feedback": "the safety of the air transport of hazardous materials"
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the European Regulation on Air Operations as applicable to Commercial Air Transport operations. A crew member is acclimatised to the time zone where he/she is, and is rostered to start his/her Flight Duty Period (FDP) at the least restrictive time of the day. What is the maximum duration of this basic daily FDP, excluding any extensions?",
    "feedback": "13 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "When the weather conditions require an alternate aerodrome to be available on take-off, the latter shall be located, for a twin-engined aircraft, at an equivalent distance not exceeding :",
    "feedback": "1 hour of flight at cruising speed with a single engine"
  },
  {
    "question": "Given:  g, the longitude difference Lm, the average latitude Lo, the latitude of the tangent  The transport precession is equal to :",
    "feedback": "g.sin Lm"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, the lowest minima to be used by an operator for circling with a category A aeroplane is a meteorological visibility of:",
    "feedback": "1500 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is approaching its destination and the landing is planned to take place within 30 minutes. The flight crew have 1 hour left until they reach their maximum daily Flight Duty Period (FDP). Suddenly the Commander receives a message from the Operator asking him/her to divert to another destination for maintenance purposes. Reaching this destination would take 2 hours from the present position of the aircraft, thus exceeding the maximum daily FDP for the flight crew. Could this diversion be performed?",
    "feedback": "Yes, the Commander may increase the daily FDP if unforeseen circumstances arise, in consultation with the crew"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is entering the NAT HLA Airspace and ATC advises the crew to maintain the assigned speed. The crew is aware of the fact, that the airspace is very busy and there are aircraft in all quadrants.\nWhat is the first action of the crew on entering an area with moderate to severe turbulence?",
    "feedback": "Reduce the speed to rough air speed and inform ATC"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, for a pressurised aircraft, the definition of supplemental oxygen is:",
    "feedback": "oxygen supplied to the aeroplane occupants in the case of cabin pressurisation failure"
  },
  {
    "question": "A jet transport aeroplane is landing at an airport situated close to a noise sensitive area at 23:59 UTC. Noise Abatement Procedures are in force from 22:00 to 03:00 UTC. Use of reverse thrust is ......",
    "feedback": "allowed as the Noise Abatement Procedures permit this during landing"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is one main factor to be remembered when considering the ditching of an aircraft?",
    "feedback": "On the high seas, it is usually best to ditch parallel to, and on top of the primary swell system, except in high wind conditions"
  },
  {
    "question": "The field of application of the Minimum Equipment List (MEL) is defined by a phase of flight operation. The commander must use the limitations provided by the MEL:",
    "feedback": "at the parking area prior to the aircraft taxiing"
  },
  {
    "question": "You are on final approach to land at a coastal airfield, with a high mountain situated nearby and little traffic. A go-around was initiated after observing excessive autothrottle inputs, unusual pitch changes, and a sudden decrease in indicated airspeed.\nBased on the information given, which is the most probable cause?",
    "feedback": "Low-level windshear"
  },
  {
    "question": "For three- and four-engined aeroplanes, the take-off alternate, if required, shall be located (in still air conditions) within:",
    "feedback": "two hours flight time at one engine inoperative cruising speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following will shorten the applicable holdover time (HOT) for de-icing/anti-icing procedures?\n1) High wind velocity2) Low wind velocity3) Ambient temperature above 0 degrees Celsius4) High relative humidity5) Aeroplane skin temperature below the ambient temperature6) A low concentration of anti-icing fluide in the anti-icing fluid/water mix",
    "feedback": "1, 4, 5, 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an airplane with a  tyre pressure of 8 bars, there is a risk of dynamic hydroplaning as soon as the :\n\n1- water height is equal to the depth of the tyre grooves.\n2- speed is greater than 96 kt.\n3- water height is equal to the half of the depth of the tyre grooves.\n4- speed is greater than 127 kt.\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1 and 2."
  },
  {
    "question": "When an aircraft flies into a horizontal tail wind gust the aircraft tends :",
    "feedback": "to descend"
  },
  {
    "question": "Information concerning evacuation procedures can be found in the :",
    "feedback": "operation manual."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS and assuming the following circumstances:\n- A multi-engine category B aeroplane able to, in the event of a critical power unit failure at any point during take-off, either stop or continue the take-off to a height of 1500 ft above the aerodrome while clearing obstacles by the required margins- An aerodrome equipped with runway edge and centre line lighting and multiple RVR information- an acceptable alternate aerodrome is available\nThe minimum RVR/Visibility required for take-off is:",
    "feedback": "150 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "The reference document you shall use when a piece of equipment on your aircraft fails during taxi is:",
    "feedback": "the operation manual's chapter \"Abnormal and Emergency Procedures\""
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the European Regulation on Air Operations as applicable to Commercial Air Transport operations. An aeroplane is being operated with an augmented flight crew. Due to unforeseen circumstances in flight operations, a Commander has to increase the Flight Duty Period (FDP). The Commander is permitted to increase this FDP by a maximum of how many hours?",
    "feedback": "3 hours"
  },
  {
    "question": "Considering the two holds of an aircraft :\nEach one consists of 4 compartments to accommodate freight pallets or luggage containers.\nYou are asked to load :\n2 pallets of live animals marked \"AVI\"\n2 luggage containers marked \"BAG\"\n1 mortal remains marked \"HUM\"\n1 pallet of food product marked \"EAT\"\n1 pallet of radioactive materials marked \"RRY\"\n1 pallet of toxic materials marked \"RHF\"\nThe locations still vacant shall be marked \"XXX\"\nAccording to the table of compatibility of special freight and hazardous materials given in the appendix, the most operational distribution in the holds shall be :",
    "feedback": "Hold 1 : BAG - RHF - HUM - RRY\nHold 2 : AVI - AVI - BAG - EAT"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to ICAO Annex 6 Part I, a Commercial Air Transport Operator of aeroplanes is required to establish a flight data analysis programme as part of the Safety Management System when operating ....",
    "feedback": "one or more aeroplanes with a maximum certificated take-off mass in excess of 27000 kg"
  },
  {
    "question": "Your aircraft is equipped with steel brakes. How will you gain maximum performance when you taxi to the runway?",
    "feedback": "Frequent light taps because brakes are limited by heat"
  },
  {
    "question": "You will use a powder fire-extinguisher for:\n\n1. a paper fire\n2. a plastic fire\n3. a hydrocarbon fire\n4. an electrical fire\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "EASA AIR OPS applies to:",
    "feedback": "the operation by a EASA state member of any civil commercial transport aeroplane"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regarding all weather operations, if Vat is from 121 kt to 140 kt, the aeroplane is in Category:",
    "feedback": "C"
  },
  {
    "question": "The M.E.L. (Minimum Equipment List) is drawn up by :",
    "feedback": "the operator"
  },
  {
    "question": "In case of an unexpected encounter with windshear, you will:\n\n1. set the maximum take-off thrust\n2. increase the pitch-up attitude up to the limit actuating the stick shaker\n3. pull in the drag devices (gear and flaps)\n4. keep the airplane's current configuration\n5. try to reach the maximum lift-to-drag ratio\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The observations and studies conducted on the behavior of birds on the ground, ahead of an aircraft taking off and having reached an average speed of 135 kt, show that birds fly away :",
    "feedback": "about two seconds beforehand"
  },
  {
    "question": "The standby power supply powering the standby artificial horizon must be operable on board any aircraft of more than 5700 kg or more than 9 passengers during at least :",
    "feedback": "30 minutes."
  },
  {
    "question": "You are about to land. What is the best runway without the risk for wake turbulence?",
    "feedback": "RWY 33R, northerly wind 10 kt, light airplane ahead of you"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which part of the Operations Manual can you find information regarding contaminated runways?",
    "feedback": "Part B"
  },
  {
    "question": "In case of an engine nozzle fire while on ground you :",
    "feedback": "carry out a dry cranking."
  },
  {
    "question": "Consider the applicable operational requirements on task specialists' responsibilities. Task specialists' duties shall be specified ....",
    "feedback": "in the SOPs (Standard Operating Procedures)"
  },
  {
    "question": "A flight via the Shannon-Gander great circle with no MNPS certification can be planned:",
    "feedback": "At FL280 or below"
  },
  {
    "question": "Apart from fire extinguishers the following equipment for the fire fighting is typically located on board:",
    "feedback": "crash axes or crowbars."
  },
  {
    "question": "On overwater flights, an operator shall not operate an aeroplane at a distance away from land, which is suitable for making a emergency landing greater than that corresponding to :",
    "feedback": "400 NM or 120 minutes at cruising speed."
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is on the glidepath and there is a microburst ahead that is to the right of the glidepath. What will this initially result in?",
    "feedback": "Increasing airspeed, left drift and a slight decrease in the rate of descent"
  },
  {
    "question": "For the purpose of wake turbulence separation, what is the ICAO minimum radar separation distance if a heavy aeroplane is following directly behind another heavy aeroplance on the approach to the same runway ?",
    "feedback": "7.4 km (4 NM)"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming a multi-engine land aeroplane with 60 persons on board. The cruising speed is 180 kt. The aeroplane is capable of continuing the flight with the critical power unit becoming inoperative. The track will overfly water for a distance of 380 NM from land which is suitable for making an emergency landing.  According to EASA AIR OPS, the minimum number of life rafts shall be:",
    "feedback": "3 life rafts of 30-seat capacity"
  },
  {
    "question": "Assuming 60 passengers on board a land aeroplane. The intended track will overfly water for a distance of 80 NM from the shore. According to EASA AIR OPS, the minimum number of passenger life jackets to be on board is:",
    "feedback": "60"
  },
  {
    "question": "An operator must ensure that, for the duration of each flight, be kept on the ground a copy of the :",
    "feedback": "operation flight plan."
  },
  {
    "question": "The accumulation of frost, snow or ice on an aircraft in flight induces an increase in the:",
    "feedback": "stalling speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight, the Senior Cabin Crew Member informs the flight crew that a passenger is using a Portable Electronic Device PED (a satellite phone) which could adversely affect the aircraft electronic systems. Which option is correct?",
    "feedback": "If the PED could interfere with the aircraft systems it must be turned off"
  },
  {
    "question": "In public transport, prior to take-off in icing conditions, the captain must check that:",
    "feedback": "external surfaces are free from any ice accretion which may impede the airplane performance and manoeuvrability, except within the limits specified by the flight manual."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the expected braking action on the runway when the friction coefficient is 0.4 or higher?",
    "feedback": "Good"
  },
  {
    "question": "Under the European Regulations on Civil Aviation, concerning oversight and enforcement, who should conduct investigations, including ramp inspections, to prevent the continuation of an infringement?",
    "feedback": "The member states"
  },
  {
    "question": "The most efficient bird scaring technique generally available is :",
    "feedback": "broadcasting of recorded distress calls"
  },
  {
    "question": "What happens when an aeroplane encounters a downdraft during an approach?",
    "feedback": "The aeroplane's angle of attack decreases"
  },
  {
    "question": "An engine fire warning will switch on the relevant fire shut off-handle.\nThe fire shut-off handle will be switched off when:",
    "feedback": "fire is no longer detected."
  },
  {
    "question": "A fast decompression is recognizable by the following elements:\n\n1. mist in the cabin\n2. blast towards the exterior of the aircraft\n3. expansion of body gases\n4. blast of air released violently from the lungs\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "A light aircraft is about to depart from a busy aerodrome. Simultaneous runway operations for departure are in progress, and clearance delivery asks the pilot which runway he/she prefers for departure. Considering the wind information given below, which runway should the pilot choose to reduce the potential of wake turbulence effects?\nRunway 25R: Wind variable at 5 ktRunway 25C: Wind is calmRunway 25L: Wind is westerly at 3 ktRunway 18: Wind is south-westerly at 12 kt",
    "feedback": "Runway 18"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, for operations under IFR or at night the minimum flight crew is 2 pilots for:",
    "feedback": "all turbopropeller aeroplanes with a maximum approved passenger seating configuration of more than 9 and for all turbojet aeroplanes"
  },
  {
    "question": "What special considerations have to be observed when transporting packages containing Dangerous Goods which might react dangerously with one another?\nThese packages must ......",
    "feedback": "not be stowed next to each other"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the transponder code to be used by an aircraft that is subject to unlawful interference (hijacked) is :",
    "feedback": "7500"
  },
  {
    "question": "MNPS airspace in the applicable areas of the North Atlantic is defined between the following flight levels:",
    "feedback": "FL 285 and FL 420"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, at least one of the following hand fire extinguishers must be conveniently located on the flight deck:",
    "feedback": "a Halon fire extinguisher or equivalent"
  },
  {
    "question": "For two-engined aeroplanes not approved for ETOPS, the take-off alternate, if required, shall be located (in still air conditions) within:",
    "feedback": "one hour flight time at one engine inoperative cruising speed"
  },
  {
    "question": "In case of a cargo compartment fire, the system which should be switched off, is generally the:",
    "feedback": "ventilation of the cargo compartment"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an operation in MNPS airspace along notified special routes unless otherwise specified, an aircraft must be equipped with at least:",
    "feedback": "One Long Range Navigation System (LRNS)."
  },
  {
    "question": "You will use a halon extinguisher for a fire of:\n\n1 - solids (fabric, plastic, ...)\n2 - liquids (alcohol, gasoline, ...)\n3 - gas\n4 - metals (aluminium, magnesium, ...)\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1,2,3"
  },
  {
    "question": "The fire extinguisher types which may be used on class A fires are:\n1 - H2O\n2 - CO2\n3 - dry-chemical\n4 - halon\n\nWhich of the following combinations contains all of the correct statements?",
    "feedback": "1 - 2 - 3 - 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "There is a hospital in close proximity of the airport. An aircraft is following the NADP 1 procedure. Which of the following statements is correct regarding acceleration and cleaning up the aircraft?",
    "feedback": "At no more than an altitude equivalent to 900 m (3000 ft) above aerodrome elevation, while maintaining a positive rate of climb, accelerate and retract flaps/slats on schedule"
  },
  {
    "question": "When does the anti-icing holdover time begin on a 2 step procedure?",
    "feedback": "From the start of the anti-icing procedure"
  },
  {
    "question": "A jet-powered aircraft, flying above the optimum altitude will have :",
    "feedback": "reduced range"
  },
  {
    "question": "Astronomic precession :",
    "feedback": "causes the gyro axis to spin to the left in the southern hemisphere"
  },
  {
    "question": "The regulatory green navigation light is located on the starboard wing tip, with a coverage angle of :",
    "feedback": "110°."
  },
  {
    "question": "A category I precision approach (CAT I) is an approach which may be carried out with a runway visual range of at least :",
    "feedback": "550 m"
  },
  {
    "question": "A CO2 fire extinguisher can be used for:\n\n1. a paper fire\n2. a hydrocarbon fire\n3. a fabric fire\n4. an electrical fire\n5. a wood fire\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4, 5"
  },
  {
    "question": "The abbreviation MNPS means :",
    "feedback": "Minimum Navigation Performance Specification"
  },
  {
    "question": "A dry-chemical type fire extinguisher is fit to fight:\n\n1- class A fires\n2- class B fires\n3- electrical source fires\n4- special fires: metals, gas, chemicals\n\nWhich of the following combinations contains all of the correct statements?",
    "feedback": "1 - 2 - 3 - 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, the public address system must be audible and intelligible at:  1) all passenger seats 2) toilets 3) cabin crew seats 4) work stations  The combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "The wake turbulence category \"Heavy\" applies to aircraft with a maximum certificated takeoff mass in excess of:",
    "feedback": "299200 lbs."
  },
  {
    "question": "In which part of the Operations Manual would you find information regarding company routes and instructions?",
    "feedback": "Part C"
  },
  {
    "question": "Information, instructions and general guidance on the transport of dangerous goods are included in the:",
    "feedback": "Operations Manual"
  },
  {
    "question": "The dangerous goods transport document, if required, shall be drawn up by :",
    "feedback": "the shipper."
  },
  {
    "question": "According to ICAO Annex 17, following an unlawful interference, who shall take adequate measures for the safety of passengers and crew of an aircraft, until their journey can be continued?",
    "feedback": "The contracting State where the aircraft is located"
  },
  {
    "question": "What might be noticeable during a slow decompression?",
    "feedback": "An increase in cabin altitude"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, an aeroplane whose maximum approved passenger seating configuration is 61 to 200 seats must be equipped with at least:",
    "feedback": "3 hand fire extinguishers conveniently located in the passenger compartment"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which document to you refer to when unlawful interference takes place over the Atlantic?",
    "feedback": "OPS manual Part A"
  },
  {
    "question": "The minimum flight crew for night transport of passengers or according to the Instrument flight rules is :",
    "feedback": "2 pilots for turbo-jet aircraft and turbo-prop aircraft with more than 9 passenger seats"
  },
  {
    "question": "For purpose of wake turbulence separation, what is the ICAO minimum radar separation time if a light aeroplance (7000 kg or less) is following a medium aeroplane (less than 136000 kg but more than 7000 kg) on the approach to landing ?",
    "feedback": "3 minutes"
  },
  {
    "question": "The validity period of a night-time organised track system in MNPS airspace is normally, at 30°W, between:",
    "feedback": "0100 UTC to 0800 UTC"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to OPS regulations, the runway condition complying with the definition of a \"wet runway\" is:",
    "feedback": "There is sufficient moisture on the runway surface to cause it to appear reflective, but without significant areas of standing water"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the definition for horizontal wind shear?",
    "feedback": "The change of the horizontal wind vector with horizontal distance, as might be determined by two or more anemometers mounted at the same height along a runway"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane is intended to be operated at FL 390. Given that:  Maximum approved passenger seating configuration = 230 Number of seats on board = 200 Scheduled number of passengers on board = 180  According to EASA AIR OPS, the minimum required number of cabin oxygen masks (dispensing units) shall be:",
    "feedback": "220"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who has the responsibility for establishing operating procedures for noise abatement purposes during instrument flight in compliance with ICAO PANS OPS the :",
    "feedback": "operator"
  },
  {
    "question": "You will use a CO2 fire-extinguisher for :\n\n1. a paper fire\n2. a plastic fire\n3. a hydrocarbon fire\n4. an electrical fire\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1,2,3,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where can you find information about flying in known icing conditions of your complex motor-powered aircraft?",
    "feedback": "OPS manual Part B"
  },
  {
    "question": "During a flight to Europe, scheduled in MNPS airspace, you expect to cross the 30°W meridian at 1330 UTC; you will normally be:",
    "feedback": "in a day-time organised track system"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS and with the exception of amphibians and seaplanes, the carriage of a life jacket for each person on board is compulsory when the aeroplane is:  1) cruising at such a distance from the shore that it would not be able to return in the case of an engine failure 2) is flying over water at a distance from the shore of more than 50 NM 3) is using departure and arrival paths over water and when a ditching probability exists 4) is flying over a stretch of water at more than 40 NM off shore  The combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Refer to commercial aircraft operations: In what part of the Operations Manual would you find general de-icing procedures about the company?",
    "feedback": "Part A"
  },
  {
    "question": "Regulation (EC) No 300/2008 establishes common rules/standards with regard to security. Which of the following is correct?",
    "feedback": "All civil airports (no military facilities) are required to follow the standards"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, an aeroplane whose maximum approved passenger seating configuration is 401 to 500 seats must be equipped with at least:",
    "feedback": "6 hand fire extinguishers conveniently located in the passenger compartment"
  },
  {
    "question": "A flight is to depart from an airport with runways 09 and 27. Suface wind is 270/05; an inversion is reported at 300 feet with turbulence and wind shear. The wind just above the inversion is 090/30. What is the safest departure procedure?",
    "feedback": "Depart runway 09 with a tailwind"
  },
  {
    "question": "Mist in the cabin, pressure and temperature drop characterise:",
    "feedback": "a rapid depressurisation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The ascent or descent through MNPS (Minimum Navigation Performance Specification) airspace of a non MNPS certified aircraft is :",
    "feedback": "authorized under radar control if the aircraft is in VHF contact with the MNPS controller"
  },
  {
    "question": "The MEL (Minimum Equipment List) can be changed by:",
    "feedback": "the operator"
  },
  {
    "question": "Arriving at the entry point of the MNPS airspace (except Shanwick Oceanic) and not having yet received the oceanic clearance, the crew:",
    "feedback": "keeps flying in accordance with the curren flight plan"
  },
  {
    "question": "Aircraft using a VFR flight plan in controlled airspace shall be equipped: (Annex 6, Part I)",
    "feedback": "As is necessary for aircraft that operate in accordance with instrument flight rules."
  },
  {
    "question": "Two aeroplanes are arriving from the same direction to land at an airport where making a straight-in approach and landing with a tailwind (within operational limits) will shorten the flight time by a few minutes. One of the aeroplanes is equipped with carbon brakes and the other with steel brakes. Which of the following statements is correct?\nThe aeroplane with....",
    "feedback": "carbon brakes may have a benefit landing with a tailwind as carbon brakes remain efficient at high temperatures and the wear is mainly determined by the number of applications"
  },
  {
    "question": "If a flight is planned to operate along the whole length of one of the organised tracks, the intended organised track should be defined in items of the FPL by :",
    "feedback": "the abbreviation \"NAT\" followed by the code letter assigned to the track."
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, an operator must ensure that the MDH for a VOR approach is not lower than:",
    "feedback": "300 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "Whenever possible, what initial action should a pilot take if, following unlawful interference, the aircraft must depart from the assigned track or cruising level without being able to contact an Air Traffice Service provider?",
    "feedback": "Attempt to broadcast warnings on the VHF channel in use or the VHF emergency frequency"
  },
  {
    "question": "As regards the detection of bird strike hazard, the pilot's means of information and prevention are:\n\n1 - ATIS.\n2 - NOTAMs.\n3 - BIRDTAMs.\n4 - Weather radar.\n5 - The report by another crew.\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements is :",
    "feedback": "1,2,3,5"
  },
  {
    "question": "The fire extinguisher types which may be used to fight fire on carbonaceous materials are:\n\n1) H2O\n2) CO2\n3) dry-chemical\n4) Halon\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3, 4"
  },
  {
    "question": "After take-off, an aircraft is subjected to windshear with a decreasing head wind. In the absence of a pilot action, the aircraft :\n\n1- flies above the climb-out path\n2- flies below the climb-out path\n3- has an increasing true airspeed\n4- has a decreasing true airspeed\n\nThe combination of correct statements is :",
    "feedback": "2,4."
  },
  {
    "question": "During a landing approach, the aircraft is subjected to windshear with a decreasing head wind. In the absence of a pilot action, the aircraft :\n\n1. flies above the glide path\n2. flies below the glide path\n3. has an increasing true airspeed\n4. has a decreasing true airspeed\n\nThe combination of correct statements is :",
    "feedback": "2,4"
  },
  {
    "question": "During the loading of dangerous goods into an aircraft, you notice that a package is damaged. This package:",
    "feedback": "Shall be removed from the aircraft, under the Operator's responsibility"
  },
  {
    "question": "For an airplane with a  tyre pressure of 10 bars, there is a risk of dynamic hydroplaning as soon as the  :\n\n1- water height is equal to the depth of the tyre grooves.\n2- speed is greater than 104 kt.\n3- water height is equal to the half of the depth of the tyre grooves.\n4- speed is greater than 96 kt.\n\nThe combination regrouping all the correct statements i :",
    "feedback": "1 and 2."
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the relationship between MEL and MMEL?",
    "feedback": "The Master Minimum Equipment List can be less restricting than the Minimum Equipment List"
  },
  {
    "question": "Due to a cabin pressurization defect the maximum differential pressure is limited to 3 psi. Assuming the oxygen masks will be deployed at 14'000 feet, the maximum achievabale flight altitude is approximately:",
    "feedback": "24'500 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, who is responsible for establishing Aerodrome Operating Minima for each aerodrome planned to be used for commercial purposes?",
    "feedback": "The Operator"
  },
  {
    "question": "Select the correct line which might be seen in a SNOWTAM when the estimated surface friction is reported:",
    "feedback": "H)5/4/4"
  },
  {
    "question": "A Halon fire extinguisher should be used on a fire of:\n\n1) paper, fabric, plastic\n2) flammable liquids\n3) flammable gases\n4) metals\n\nThe combination that regroups all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "A list of dangerous goods, which may not be transported by air, can be found in:",
    "feedback": "the Technical Instructions for the Safe Transport of Dangerous Goods by Air"
  },
  {
    "question": "Flights within NAT region shall be conducted in accordance with IFR when:",
    "feedback": "Operating at or above FL 60 or 2000 ft whichever is higher."
  },
  {
    "question": "Of the following actions listed, which would be the most appropriate if microbursts are forecast and observed immediately prior to an approach for landing?",
    "feedback": "Hold until conditions improve or divert to the alternate"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, in an aeroplane in which fuses are used, the number of spare fuses available for use in flight must be at least:",
    "feedback": "10% of the number of fuses of each rating or 3 of each rating, whichever is the greater"
  },
  {
    "question": "According to ICAO noise abatement procedures during landing:",
    "feedback": "shall not prohibit the use of reverse thrust"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, regarding the first aid oxygen, the supply of undiluted oxygen carried on board a pressurised aeroplane with 8 passengers operated at pressure altitude 27000 ft, shall be sufficient for at least:",
    "feedback": "1 passenger for the remainder of the flight after cabin depressurisation when the cabin altitude exceeds 8000 ft"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aircraft is descending in conditions of little or no wind. Upon contact with the ground, the trailing vortices travel horizontally away from each other at a height approximately equal to what proportion of the generating aircraft's wing span?",
    "feedback": "Half the wing span"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, an aeroplane whose maximum approved passenger seating configuration is 201 to 300 seats must be equipped with at least:",
    "feedback": "4 hand fire extinguishers conveniently located in the passenger compartment"
  },
  {
    "question": "If a piece of equipment on your public transport aircraft becomes inoperatire while you are still parked at the gate the reference document you should use before making the decision to proceed is:",
    "feedback": "the Operations Manual under the heading \"MEL\""
  },
  {
    "question": "According to EASA AIR OPS, which of the following is the correct definition of \"wet lease\"?",
    "feedback": "The aircraft is operated under the AOC of the lessor"
  },
  {
    "question": "In accordance with EASA AIR OPS, an operator shall ensure that a copy for the operational flight plan is stored in an acceptable form for at least:",
    "feedback": "3 months"
  },
  {
    "question": "An adequate ETOPS en-route alternate aerodrome should be available within the Operator's approved diversion time....",
    "feedback": "or a diversion time based on the MEL-generated serviceability status of the aeroplane, whichever is shorter"
  },
  {
    "question": "An aeroplane which has a maximum certificated take-off mass over 5700 kg, shall be equipped with a cockpit voice recorder capable of retaining information recorded during at least the last:",
    "feedback": "30 minutes or 2 hours of its operation, depending upon the date of the first issue of its individual Certificate of Airworthiness"
  },
  {
    "question": "During an ILS procedure, if the reported RVR/visibility is less than the applicable minima, the approach shall not be continued beyond:",
    "feedback": "the outer marker or equivalent, or 1000 ft above the aerodrome / heliport if there is no outer marker or equivalent"
  },
  {
    "question": "A runway is considered to be contaminated when its surface is covered more than:",
    "feedback": "25% with compacted snow"
  },
  {
    "question": "The aircraft is of Category A. The runway has edge lights and high intensity centre line lights. There is an accessible alternate aerodrome and the two pilot crew is IFR qualified on type. The minimum horizontal visibility required for take-off is:",
    "feedback": "200 m."
  },
  {
    "question": "The Master Minimum Equipment List (MMEL) defines the equipment which can be inoperative when undertaking a flight and the conditions under which this allowance can be accepted. This MMEL is drawn up by:",
    "feedback": "the manufacturer and approved by the certification authority"
  },
  {
    "question": "A polar stereographic chart has a grid printed over it which is parallel to the meridian 054°W, with Grid North in the direction of the North geographic pole.\nAn aircraft is following a true course of 330°.\nAt position 80°N 140°E, its grid heading (GH) with this system will be :",
    "feedback": "136°."
  },
  {
    "question": "The wake turbulence is the most severe when the aircraft is :\n\n1. slow\n2. heavy\n3. in a clean configuration\n4. flying with a high thrust\n\nThe combination regrouping all of the correct statements is:",
    "feedback": "1, 2, 3"
  },
  {
    "question": "Gradual decompression is caused by:\n1) Window leak2) Door leak3) Window blown4) Emergency escape hatch open",
    "feedback": "1, 2"
  }
]